-RRB-/O -RRB-/O Higher/O geography/O Frye/PERSON ,/O Alex/PERSON Everett/PERSON ,/O 1859-1936/O 1st/O electronic/O edition/O 1003/O KB/O Austin/LOCATION ,/O Tex./LOCATION ./O The/O University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Texas/ORGANIZATION Libraries/ORGANIZATION 2004/O Alexis/PERSON Everett/PERSON Frye/PERSON Higher/O geography/O Boston/ORGANIZATION London/ORGANIZATION Ginn/ORGANIZATION Co./ORGANIZATION 1903/O viii/O ,/O 195/O ,/O viii/PERSON ,/O 16/O p./O ill./O ,/O maps/O 32/O cm/O ./O 03-1806/O 17540901/O UTNETCAT/O record/O ``/O Supplement/O to/O Frye/PERSON 's/O geography/O :/O Texas/LOCATION by/O Frederic/PERSON W./PERSON Simonds/PERSON ''/O Dewey/PERSON Decimal/O Classification/O Library/O of/O Congress/ORGANIZATION Subject/O Headings/O English/O G127/O F923/O T42/O Geography/O --/O Textbooks/O --/O 1870-1945/O Physical/O geography/O Paleontology/O --/O Early/O works/O to/O 1900/O Oceanography/O Climatology/O Meteorology/LOCATION Botany/LOCATION Zoology/O Anthropology/O Minerology/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O --/O 1865-1900/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION --/O Politics/O and/O government/O Canada/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Mexico/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Central/LOCATION America/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O West/LOCATION Indies/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O South/LOCATION America/LOCATION --/O Desctription/PERSON and/O travel/O Europe/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Asia/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Africa/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Australia/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Puerto/LOCATION Rico/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Virgin/O Islands/O of/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O Texas/LOCATION --/O Description/O and/O travel/O HIGHER/O GEOGRAPHY/O BY/O ALEXIS/PERSON EVERETT/PERSON FRYE/PERSON Former/O Superintendent/O of/O Schools/O of/O Cuba/LOCATION AUTHOR/O OF/O ``/O CHILD/O AND/O NATURE/O ,/O ''/O ``/O BROOKS/O AND/O BROOK/O BASINS/O ,/O ''/O ``/O PRIMARY/O GEOGRAPHY/O ,/O ''/O ``/O ELEMENTS/O OF/O GEOGRAPHY/O ,/O ''/O ``/O HOME/O AND/O SCHOOL/O ATLAS/O ,/O ''/O ``/O TEACHERS/O ''/O MANUAL/O OF/O METHODS/O IN/O GEOGRAPHY/O ,/O ''/O ETC./LOCATION ./O BOSTON/LOCATION ,/O U.S.A./LOCATION ,/O AND/O LONDON/LOCATION GINN/PERSON COMPANY/O ,/O PUBLISHERS/O The/O Athenum/O Press/O 1903/O PREFACE/O Geography/O ./O In/O this/O book/O man/O is/O the/O central/O thought/O ./O Every/O line/O of/O type/O ,/O every/O picture/O ,/O every/O map/O ,/O has/O been/O prepared/O with/O a/O single/O purpose/O ,/O namely/O ,/O to/O present/O the/O earth/O as/O the/O home/O of/O man/O ,/O to/O describe/O and/O locate/O the/O natural/O features/O ,/O climates/O and/O products/O that/O largely/O determine/O his/O industries/O and/O commerce/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O his/O civic/O and/O other/O relations/O ,/O thus/O bringing/O REASON/O to/O bear/O on/O the/O work/O ./O Commerce/O ./O A/O geography/O that/O seeks/O to/O lay/O a/O broad/O basis/O for/O the/O study/O of/O nations/O must/O throw/O a/O strong/O searchlight/O upon/O their/O commercial/O relations/O ./O Commerce/O and/O the/O related/O industries/O take/O a/O leading/O place/O in/O this/O book/O ,/O those/O of/O our/O own/O country/O being/O illustrated/O by/O many/O maps/O -LRB-/O see/O pages/O 76-85/O -RRB-/O ,/O the/O originals/O of/O which/O were/O prepared/O expressly/O for/O this/O series/O of/O Geographies/O ,/O by/O Mr./PERSON Henry/PERSON Gannett/PERSON ,/O Chief/O Geographer/O of/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ./O Physical/O Features/O ./O The/O intelligent/O study/O of/O a/O country/O 's/O resources/O must/O be/O based/O on/O its/O physical/O features/O and/O climate/O ./O For/O this/O reason/O the/O surface-forms/O and/O climate/O of/O the/O various/O parts/O of/O the/O world/O are/O fully/O treated/O in/O the/O text/O and/O pictures/O ./O Much/O care/O has/O also/O been/O given/O to/O the/O relief/O maps/O -LRB-/O see/O pages/O 16/O and/O 68-69/O -RRB-/O ./O Illustrations/O ./O Nearly/O all/O the/O pictures/O in/O this/O book/O were/O engraved/O directly/O from/O photographs/O ./O To/O the/O selection/O and/O grouping/O of/O subjects/O for/O the/O photographs/O ,/O the/O author/O has/O given/O full/O as/O much/O time/O and/O care/O as/O to/O the/O text/O itself/O ./O The/O aim/O has/O been/O to/O present/O characteristic/O or/O typical/O forms/O that/O are/O educative/O ./O Topics/O ./O The/O work/O is/O presented/O in/O topics/O in/O such/O order/O as/O will/O enable/O pupils/O to/O reason/O from/O one/O step/O to/O another/O ./O Pupils/O should/O find/O out/O what/O the/O text/O tells/O about/O each/O topic/O and/O should/O be/O able/O to/O state/O the/O leading/O facts/O ,/O not/O in/O the/O words/O of/O the/O book/O ,/O but/O in/O their/O own/O language/O ./O Teachers/O should/O question/O pupils/O upon/O topics/O ./O Examinations/O should/O be/O based/O on/O topics/O broad/O enough/O to/O test/O thought/O ./O Helps/O ./O Many/O questions/O are/O placed/O under/O the/O HELPS/O at/O the/O end/O of/O lessons/O to/O guide/O pupils/O in/O their/O study/O ,/O by/O suggesting/O what/O parts/O of/O the/O text/O call/O for/O closest/O attention/O ./O The/O topics/O ,/O however/O ,/O afford/O a/O broader/O basis/O for/O recitation/O ./O Unity/O ./O This/O book/O holds/O the/O earth/O as/O the/O unit/O before/O the/O mind/O and/O relates/O all/O study/O to/O that/O unit/O ./O The/O memory/O is/O thus/O aided/O and/O much/O time/O is/O saved/O ./O Sizes/O of/O Type/O ./O The/O text/O which/O needs/O the/O most/O careful/O study/O is/O in/O large/O type/O ./O The/O descriptive/O matter/O in/O small/O type/O does/O not/O call/O for/O close/O study/O ,/O but/O many/O maybe/O used/O for/O supplementary/O reading/O ./O Spelling/O and/O Capitalization/O ./O In/O spelling/O and/O usage/O of/O geographic/O names/O ,/O the/O maps/O and/O text/O follow/O the/O ruling/O of/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION board/O on/O Geographic/O Names/O ./O There/O has/O long/O been/O confusion/O in/O the/O usage/O of/O capital/O letters/O ./O This/O book/O adopts/O what/O seems/O to/O be/O the/O best/O modern/O usage/O and/O allows/O the/O capital/O in/O specific/O names/O ,/O such/O as/O Rhine/O and/O Andes/O ,/O but/O not/O in/O class/O names/O ,/O such/O as/O river/O and/O plateau/O ;/O thus/O Rhine/LOCATION river/O ./O The/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION and/O Canadian/ORGANIZATION Geographic/ORGANIZATION Boards/ORGANIZATION rule/O out/O the/O apostrophe/O from/O names/O of/O places/O within/O the/O two/O countries/O ./O THE/O AUTHOR/O ./O BOSTON/LOCATION ,/O March/O ,/O 1903/O ./O COPYRIGHT/O ,/O 1895/O ,/O 1899/O ,/O 1902/O ,/O BY/O ALEXIS/PERSON EVERETT/PERSON FRYE/PERSON ./O ALL/O RIGHTS/O RESERVED/O ./O Entered/O at/O Stationers/ORGANIZATION '/O Hall/O ./O TABLE/O OF/O CONTENTS/O INTRODUCTION/O 1/O THE/ORGANIZATION EARTH/ORGANIZATION LESSON/ORGANIZATION 1/O ./O FORM/O AND/O SIZE/O OF/O THE/O EARTH/O 2/O 2/O ./O DIRECTIONS/O ON/O THE/O EARTH/O 3/O FORMS/O OF/O LAND/O AND/O WATER/O 3/O ./O THE/O LAND/O AND/O ITS/O SOIL/O 4/O 4/O ./O RAINFALL/O AND/O SPRINGS/ORGANIZATION 5/O 5/O ./O LAKES/O AND/O RIVERS/O 6/O 6/O ./O PLAINS/O 8/O 7/O ./O MOUNTAINS/O AND/O VALLEYS/O 9/O 8/O ./O VOLCANOES/O 11/O 9/O ./O WAVES/O AND/O TIDES/O 11/O 10/O ./O SHORE/O FORMS/O 12/O CONTINENTS/O AND/O OCEANS/O 11/O ./O THE/O CONTINENTS/O 14/O 12/O ./O THE/O OCEANS/O 15/O 13/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O NORTH/ORGANIZATION AMERICA/ORGANIZATION 17/O 14/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O SOUTH/ORGANIZATION AMERICA/ORGANIZATION 18/O 15/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O EUROPE/ORGANIZATION 19/O 16/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O ASIA/ORGANIZATION 20/O 17/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O AFRICA/LOCATION AND/O AUSTRALIA/ORGANIZATION 22/O CLIMATE/O OF/O THE/O EARTH/O 18/O ./O LATITUDE/O AND/O LONGITUDE/O 23/O 19/O ./O CHANGE/O OF/O SEASONS/O 25/O 20/O ./O THE/O ZONES/O 27/O 21/O ./O SEASONS/O OF/O THE/O ZONES/O 27/O 22/O ./O WINDS/O AND/O RAINFALL/O 29/O 23/O ./O OCEAN/O CURRENTS/O 32/O RACES/O OF/O MEN/O 24/O ./O THE/O BLACK/O RACE/O 33/O 25/O ./O THE/O RED/ORGANIZATION RACE/ORGANIZATION 34/O 26/O ./O THE/O BROWN/PERSON OR/O MALAY/O RACE/O 35/O 27/O ./O THE/O YELLOW/O RACE/O 36/O 28/O ./O THE/ORGANIZATION WHITE/ORGANIZATION RACE/ORGANIZATION 38/O 29/O ./O RELIGIONS/O 39/O 30/O ./O GOVERNMENTS/O 40/O ZONES/O OF/O PLANT/O LIFE/O 31/O ./O WHERE/O PLANTS/O GROW/O 42/O 32/O ./O PLANTS/O OF/O THE/O TORRID/O ZONE/O 44/O 33/O ./O PLANTS/O OF/O THE/O WARM/O TEMPERATE/O ZONES/O 47/O 34/O ./O PLANTS/O OF/O THE/O COOL/O TEMPERATE/O ZONE/O 50/O 35/O ./O PLANTS/O OF/O THE/O NORTH/O FRIGID/O ZONE/O 51/O ZONES/O OF/O ANIMAL/O LIFE/O 36/O ./O WHERE/O ANIMALS/O LIVE/O 53/O 37/O ./O DISTRIBUTION/O OF/O ANIMALS/O 54/O MINERALS/ORGANIZATION 38/O ./O MINES/O AND/O QUARRIES/O 56/O COMMERCE/ORGANIZATION 39/O ./O HIGHWAYS/O OF/O TRADE/O 59/O THE/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 40/O ./O PEOPLE/O OF/O THE/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 61/O 41/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O THE/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 64/O 42/O ./O CLIMATE/O OF/O THE/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 74/O PRODUCTS/O OF/O THE/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 43/O ./O COTTON/O 76/O 44/O ./O WHEAT/O 77/O 45/O ./O CORN/O 77/O 46/O ./O OATS/O ,/O BARLEY/O AND/O RYE/ORGANIZATION 78/O 47/O ./O TOBACCO/O 78/O 48/O ./O FORESTS/O 78/O 49/O ./O FRUIT/O 79/O 50/O ./O CATTLE/O AND/O DAIRY/O PRODUCTS/O 80/O 51/O ./O SHEEP/O AND/O WOOL/O 80/O 52/O ./O HORSES/O ,/O MULES/O AND/O HOGS/O ''/O 81/O 53/O ./O FISHERIES/O 81/O 54/O ./O COAL/O IRON/O 83/O 55/O ./O IRON/O 83/O 56/O ./O PETROLEUM/O AND/O NATURAL/O GAS/O 84/O 57/O ./O GOLD/O ,/O SILVER/O ,/O COPPER/O ,/O LEAD/O ,/O ZINC/ORGANIZATION 85/O 58/O ./O OTHER/O PRODUCTS/O 85/O 59/O ./O WILD/O ANIMALS/O OF/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION AND/ORGANIZATION ALASKA/ORGANIZATION 86/O NEW/O ENGLAND/LOCATION STATES/O 60/O ./O MAINE/LOCATION ,/O NEW/LOCATION HAMPSHIRE/LOCATION ,/O VERMONT/LOCATION ,/O MASSACHUSETTS/LOCATION ,/O RHODE/ORGANIZATION ISLAND/ORGANIZATION ,/O CONNECTICUT/ORGANIZATION 88/O 61/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O NEW/O ENGLAND/LOCATION 89/O MIDDLE/O ATLANTIC/O STATES/O 62/O ./O NEW/LOCATION YORK/LOCATION ,/O NEW/LOCATION JERSEY/LOCATION ,/O PENNSYLVANIA/LOCATION ,/O DELAWARE/LOCATION ,/O MARYLAND/LOCATION ,/O VIRGINIA/LOCATION ,/O WEST/ORGANIZATION VIRGINIA/ORGANIZATION 92/O 63/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O THE/O MIDDLE/O ATLANTIC/O STATES/O 96/O SOUTHERN/O STATES/O ,/O EASTERN/O SECTION/O 64/O ./O NORTH/LOCATION CAROLINA/LOCATION ,/O SOUTH/LOCATION CAROLINA/LOCATION ,/O GEORGIA/LOCATION ,/O FLORIDA/LOCATION ,/O ALABAMA/LOCATION ,/O MISSISSIPPI/LOCATION ,/O TENNESSEE/ORGANIZATION 98/O 65/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O SOUTHERN/O STATES/O ,/O EASTERN/O SECTION/O 99/O SOUTHERN/O STATES/O ,/O WESTERN/O SECTION/O 66/O ./O LOUISIANA/LOCATION ,/O TEXAS/LOCATION ,/O ARKANSAS/LOCATION ,/O INDIAN/O TERRITORY/O ,/O OKLAHOMA/LOCATION 103/O 67/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O SOUTHERN/O STATES/O ,/O WESTERN/O SECTION/O 104/O CENTRAL/O STATES/O ,/O EASTERN/O SECTION/O 68/O ./O OHIO/LOCATION ,/O INDIANA/LOCATION ,/O ILLINOIS/LOCATION ,/O MICHIGAN/LOCATION ,/O WISCONSIN/LOCATION ,/O KENTUCKY/LOCATION 106/O 69/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O CENTRAL/O STATES/O ,/O EASTERN/O SECTION/O 108/O CENTRAL/O STATES/O ,/O WESTERN/O SECTION/O 70/O ./O MINNESOTA/LOCATION ,/O IOWA/LOCATION ,/O MISSOURI/LOCATION ,/O KANSAS/LOCATION ,/O NEBRASKA/LOCATION ,/O SOUTH/LOCATION DAKOTA/LOCATION ,/O NORTH/LOCATION DAKOTA/LOCATION 111/O 71/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O CENTRAL/O STATES/O ,/O WESTERN/O SECTION/O 112/O WESTERN/O STATES/O 72/O ./O MONTANA/LOCATION ,/O WYOMING/LOCATION ,/O COLORADO/LOCATION ,/O NEW/LOCATION MEXICO/LOCATION 115/O 73/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O THE/O ROCKY/O MOUNTAIN/O STATES/O 116/O 74/O ./O IDAHO/LOCATION ,/O UTAH/LOCATION ,/O NEVADA/LOCATION ,/O ARIZONA/LOCATION 116/O 75/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O PLATEAU/O STATES/O 118/O 76/O ./O CALIFORNIA/LOCATION ,/O OREGON/LOCATION ,/O WASHINGTON/LOCATION 119/O 77/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O PACIFIC/O COAST/O STATES/O 120/O DETACHED/O PARTS/O OF/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 78/O ./O ALASKA/LOCATION 120/O 79/O ./O HAWAIIAN/O ISLANDS/O 123/O 80/O ./O PHILIPPINE/O ISLANDS/O 124/O 81/O ./O OTHER/O ISLAND/O POSSESSIONS/O IN/O THE/O PACIFIC/O 125/O 82/O ./O PORTO/LOCATION RICO/O AND/O VIRGIN/O ISLANDS/O 126/O GOVERNMENT/O OF/O UNITED/ORGANIZATION STATES/ORGANIZATION 83/O ./O FORM/O OF/O GOVERNMENT/O 128/O OTHER/O COUNTRIES/O OF/O NORTH/ORGANIZATION AMERICA/ORGANIZATION 84/O ./O CANADA/LOCATION ,/O NEWFOUNDLAND/LOCATION AND/O NORTHERN/O ISLANDS/O 129/O 85/O ./O MEXICO/LOCATION 132/O 86/O ./O CENTRAL/O AMERICA/LOCATION 133/O 87/O ./O WEST/LOCATION INDIES/LOCATION 133/O SOUTH/ORGANIZATION AMERICA/ORGANIZATION 88/O ./O ANDES/O HIGHLAND/O 137/O 89/O ./O HIGHLANDS/O OF/O BRAZIL/LOCATION AND/O GUIANA/O 140/O 90/O ./O SELVAS/O ,/O PAMPAS/O AND/O LLANOS/ORGANIZATION 140/O 91/O ./O CLIMATE/O 141/O 92/O ./O PLANT/O LIFE/O 141/O 93/O ./O ANIMAL/O LIFE/O 142/O 94/O ./O PEOPLE/O 142/O 95/O ./O COUNTRIES/O AND/O CITITES/O 143/O EUROPE/ORGANIZATION 96/O ./O HIGHLANDS/O OF/O EUROPE/LOCATION 145/O 97/O ./O LOWLANDS/O OF/O EUROPE/LOCATION 150/O 98/O ./O THE/O BRITISH/O ISLES/O 151/O 99/O ./O CLIMATE/O 152/O 100/O ./O PLANT/O LIFE/O 152/O 101/O ./O PEOPLE/O 153/O 102/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O THE/O BRITISH/O ISLES/O 153/O 103/O ./O COUNTRIES/O AND/O CITIES/O OF/O LOWLAND/LOCATION EUROPE/LOCATION ,/O WESTERN/O PART/O 156/O 104/O ./O MEDITERRANEAN/O COUNTRIES/O AND/O CITIES/O 158/O 105/O ./O OTHER/O COUNTRIES/O AND/O CITIES/O OF/O EUROPE/LOCATION 159/O ASIA/LOCATION 106/O ./O HIGHLAND/O REGIONS/O 161/O 107/O ./O ARTIC/O AND/O CASPIAN/O SLOPES/O 165/O 108/O ./O PACIFIC/LOCATION SLOPE/O 165/O 109/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O INDIA/LOCATION 166/O 110/O ./O ASIATIC/O ISLANDS/O 167/O 111/O ./O CLIMATE/O 168/O 112/O ./O PLANT/O LIFE/O 169/O 113/O ./O ANIMALS/O OF/O NORTHERN/LOCATION ASIA/LOCATION AND/O EUROPE/LOCATION 170/O 114/O ./O ANIMALS/O OF/O SOUTHEAST/LOCATION ASIA/LOCATION AND/O THE/O EAST/O INDIES/LOCATION 171/O 115/O ./O PEOPLE/O 171/O 116/O ./O COUNTRIES/O AND/O CITIES/O 172/O AFRICA/O 117/O ./O SURFACE/O OF/O AFRICA/LOCATION 175/O 118/O ./O CLIMATE/O 181/O 119/O ./O PLANT/O LIFE/O 181/O 120/O ./O ANIMAL/O LIFE/O 182/O 121/O ./O PEOPLE/O 182/O 122/O ./O COUNTRIES/O AND/O CITIES/O 183/O AUSTRALIA/LOCATION 123/O ./O SURFACE/O AND/O CLIMATE/O 185/O 124/O ./O PLANT/O LIFE/O 186/O 125/O ./O ANIMAL/O LIFE/O 186/O 126/O ./O PEOPLE/O 188/O 127/O ./O CITIES/O OF/O AUSTRALIA/LOCATION 188/O 129/O ./O NEW/LOCATION ZEALAND/LOCATION AND/O OTHER/O ISLANDS/O 189/O SUPPLEMENT/O STATISTICAL/O TABLES/O i-v/O PRONOUNCING/O VOCABULARY/O vi-viii/O INDEX/O TO/O TEXT/O AND/O MAPS/O NOTE/O :/O All/O figures/O refer/O to/O pages/O ./O Map/O pages/O are/O marked/O thus/O ,/O 179/O ;/O picture/O pages/O are/O marked/O thus/O ,/O 1/O \*/O ./O Look/O first/O for/O pages/O in/O full/O face/O type/O -LRB-/O 174/O -RRB-/O ;/O less/O important/O pages/O are/O in/O light/O face/O type/O -LRB-/O 173/O -RRB-/O ./O A/O Abyssinia/LOCATION 178/O ,/O 179/O ./O Acapulco/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Aconcagua/LOCATION 138/O ,/O 139/O ./O Adelaide/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Adige/O river/O 157/O ./O Adirondack/O mts/O ./O 8/O \*/O ,/O 17/O \*/O ,/O 67/O ,/O 700/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 92/O ,/O 95/O ./O Adriatic/ORGANIZATION sea/O 157/O ./O gean/O sea/O 157/O ./O Afeurasia/ORGANIZATION 14/O ./O Afghanistan/LOCATION 164/O ,/O 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Africa/O 22/O ,/O 23/O ,/O 33/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ./O Animals/O 182/O ./O Climate/O 181/O ./O Countries/O 183/O ./O People/O 182/O ./O Plants/O 181/O ./O Political/O map/O 179/O ./O Relief/O map/O 22/O ,/O 176/O ./O Surface/O 22/O ,/O 23/O ,/O 175-180/O ./O Air/ORGANIZATION 2/O ,/O 3/O ,/O 25/O ,/O 29/O ./O Akron/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Alabama/ORGANIZATION 83/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 99,101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Alaska/LOCATION 8/O \*/O ,/O 17/O ,/O 82/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 122/O \*/O ,/O 123/O ./O Albany/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O Alberta/LOCATION 131/O ./O Albuquerque/LOCATION 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O Aleutians/O 122/O ,/O 123/O ./O Alexandria/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 183/O \*/O ./O Algeria/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Algiers/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Alhambra/LOCATION 148/O ./O Allegheny/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Allegheny/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 67/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 92/O ./O Allegheny/LOCATION plateau/O 67/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 106/O ./O Alligator/O 87/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ./O Alpaca/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ./O Alpine/O lakes/O 145/O ,/O 147/O ./O Alps/O 19/O ,/O 145/O \*/O ,/O 149/O ./O Altai/LOCATION mts/O ./O 163/O deg/O ;/O ./O Amazon/LOCATION river/O 18/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 140/O ./O America/LOCATION 2/O ,/O 44/O \*/O ,/O 54/O \*/O ./O American/O race/O ;/O see/O Red/O race/O ./O Amsterdam/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Amur/O river/O 163/O ,/O 165/O ./O Anam/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Andes/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 18/O ,/O 19/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 137/O ./O Andorra/LOCATION 147/O ,/O 157/O ./O Animal/O regions/O 43/O ,/O 52/O \*/O -/O 56/O \*/O ./O African/O 182/O ./O Australian/O 186/O ./O Northern/O 170/O ./O Oriental/O 171/O ./O South/O American/O 142/O ./O Ann/PERSON Arbor/PERSON 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Anniston/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Antarctic/O circle/O 25/O ,/O 27/O ./O Antarctic/O ocean/O 16/O ./O Ant-eater/O 142/O \*/O ./O Antelope/O 182/O \*/O ./O Anti-trades/O ;/O see/O Westerly/O ./O Antwerp/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Apennines/ORGANIZATION 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Apia/LOCATION 126/O ,/O 187/O ./O Appalachians/O 17,18/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 66/O ,/O 67/O \*/O ,/O 93/O ./O Apteryx/O 186/O \*/O ./O Arabia/O 163/O ,/O 164/O ,/O 165/O ,/O 175/O ./O Arabian/LOCATION sea/O 163/O ./O Arabs/O 21/O ,/O 22/O \*/O ,/O 39/O \*/O ,/O 183/O ./O Aral/O basin/O 163/O ./O Aral/O sea/O 163/O ,/O 165/O ./O Archangel/O 149/O ./O Arctic/O circle/O 25/O ,/O 27/O ./O Arctic/O ocean/O 16/O ./O Ardmore/ORGANIZATION 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Areas/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Argentina/LOCATION 138/O ,/O 139/O ./O Arica/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Arizona/ORGANIZATION 67/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 117/O ,/O 119/O ./O Arkansas/ORGANIZATION 79/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 103-105/O ./O 106/O ./O Arkansas/LOCATION river/O 72/O ./O Armadillo/O 142/O \*/O ./O Aryans/ORGANIZATION 38/O \*/O ,/O 39/O ./O Asheville/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Asia/LOCATION 20/O ,/O 21/O ./O Animals/O 170/O ,/O 171/O ./O Climate/O 168/O ./O Countries/O 172-175/O ./O People/O 171/O ./O Plants/O 169/O ./O Political/O map/O 163/O ,/O 173/O ./O Relief/O map/O 21/O ,/O 160/O ./O Surface/O 20/O ,/O 161-168/O ./O Asiatic/LOCATION Turkey/LOCATION ;/O see/O Turkey/LOCATION ./O Assiniboia/O 131/O ./O Assouan/O 177/O ,/O 179/O ./O Asuncion/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Atacama/LOCATION desert/O 138/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Atbara/LOCATION river/O 179/O ./O Athabasca/O 131/O ./O Athens/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Atlanta/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Atlantic/LOCATION coastal/O plain/O ;/O see/O Coastal/ORGANIZATION plains/O ./O Atlantic/LOCATION ocean/O 16/O ./O Atlas/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 178/O \*/O ,/O 179/O ./O Auckland/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Augusta/LOCATION ,/O Ga./LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Augusta/LOCATION ,/O Me/O ./O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Auk/O 170/O \*/O ./O Aurora/O 109/O ./O Austin/LOCATION 105/O ./O Australia/LOCATION 23/O ,/O 33/O \*/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 85/O ./O Animals/O 186/O ./O Climate/O 185/O ./O People/O 188/O ./O Plants/O 186/O ./O Political/O map/O 187/O ./O Relief/O map/O 23/O ,/O 184/O ./O States/O 188/O ./O Surface/O 23/O ,/O 185/O ./O Australian/O Alps/O 187/O ./O Australians/O ;/O see/O Black/PERSON race/O ./O Austria-Hungary/O 85/O ,/O 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Axis/O of/O earth/O 3/O ./O Azof/O 149/O ./O Azores/ORGANIZATION 180/O ,/O 190/O ./O B/O Baboon/O 182/O ./O Baffin/LOCATION bay/O 24/O \*/O ./O Bahama/LOCATION islands/O 132/O \*/O -135/O ./O Bahia/ORGANIZATION 139/O ,/O 143/O \*/O ./O Baku/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 150/O ,/O 175/O ./O Balearic/O islands/O 149/O ./O Balkan/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 149/O ./O Baltic/O sea/O 149/O ./O Baltimore/ORGANIZATION 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 82/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Baluchistan/LOCATION 164/O ,/O 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Bamboo/O 47/O \*/O ./O Banana/O 44/O \*/O ,/O 141/O ./O Banca/O 168/O ,/O 187/O ./O Bangkok/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Bangor/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Bank/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Newfoundland/ORGANIZATION 82/O ./O Banyan/ORGANIZATION 47/O \*/O ./O Bar/O 13/O \*/O ./O Barbados/ORGANIZATION 134/O ,/O 135/O Barcelona/ORGANIZATION 149/O ./O Barley/O 78/O ./O Barre/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Barrier/O reefs/O 187/O ./O Basin/O region/O of/O Asia/LOCATION 164/O ./O Basin/O region/O of/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 70/O ./O Basques/O 147/O ./O Batavia/LOCATION 174/O ,/O 187/O ./O Bath/O 88/O \*/O ,/O 91/O ./O Baton/O Rouge/O 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Batum/O 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Bay/O 12/O \*/O ./O Bay/LOCATION City/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Bay/O of/O Bengal/LOCATION 173/O ./O Bay/O of/O Biscay/O 147/O ,/O 149/O ./O Bay/O of/O Fundy/LOCATION 131/O ./O Bear/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Beaumont/O 103/O ,/O 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Beaver/O 6/O \*/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Bedouin/O 22/O \*/O ,/O 183/O \*/O ./O Belfast/LOCATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Belgium/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 150/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Belize/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Benares/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Ben-Nevis/O 151/O ,/O 155/O Benue/O river/O 179/O ./O Bergen/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Bering/O sea/O 72/O ./O Bering/O strait/O 72/O ./O Berlin/LOCATION 156/O \*/O ,/O 157/O ./O Bermuda/LOCATION 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Bern/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Bethlehem/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 164/O \*/O ,/O 165/O ./O Bighorn/O 66/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Big/ORGANIZATION Horn/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 72/O ./O Billiton/ORGANIZATION 168/O ,/O 187/O ./O Binghamton/ORGANIZATION 95/O ./O Birminham/LOCATION ,/O Ala./LOCATION 83/O ,/O 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Birmingham/LOCATION ,/O Eng/LOCATION ./O 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Bismarck/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Bison/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 55/O ,/O 66/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Black/O hills/O 111/O ,/O 113/O ./O Black/O mts/O ./O 67/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 101/O ./O Black/O race/O 23/O ,/O 33/O \*/O ,/O 35/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 182/O ,/O 183/O ,/O 188/O ./O Black/O sea/O 149/O ./O Blackstone/ORGANIZATION river/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Bluefields/O 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Blue/O Grass/O region/O 111/O ./O Blue/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 185/O ,/O 187/O ./O Blue/O ridge/O 67/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 95/O ./O Boa/O 142/O \*/O ./O Boar/O 170/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Boers/ORGANIZATION 184/O ./O Bogota/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Boise/LOCATION 119/O ,/O 121/O ./O Bokhara/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Bolan/PERSON pass/O 164/O ,/O 173/O ./O Bolivia/LOCATION 138/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Boma/O 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Bombay/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Bordeaux/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Borneo/LOCATION 167/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 187/O ./O Bosphorus/O 157/O ,/O 158/O \*/O ./O Boston/ORGANIZATION 60/O \*/O ,/O 76/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 88/O \*/O ,/O 89/O ,/O 91/O ./O Bradford/ORGANIZATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Brahmanists/ORGANIZATION 39/O ./O Brahmaputra/O river/O ,/O 167/O ,/O 173/O ./O Brazil/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 140/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 143/O ./O Brazilian/O highland/O 19/O ,/O 140/O ./O Breadfruit/O 44/O ./O Bridgeport/LOCATION 91/O ,/O 92/O ./O Brisbane/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O British/O Columbia/ORGANIZATION 129/O ,/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O British/O Guiana/O 139/O ./O British/O Isles/O 76/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 96/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 153/O ,/O 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O See/O also/O England/LOCATION ,/O Great/LOCATION Britain/LOCATION ,/O Ireland/LOCATION ,/O Scotland/LOCATION ,/O Wales/LOCATION ./O Brockton/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Brook/O 8/O \*/O ./O Brooklyn/ORGANIZATION 92/O \*/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O Brown/PERSON race/O 35/O ,/O 36/O \*/O ./O Brussels/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Budapest/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O \*/O ./O Buddhists/O 39/O ./O Buenos/O Aires/O 139/O ,/O 143/O ./O Buffalo/ORGANIZATION 95/ORGANIZATION ,/O 96/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Buffaloes/O 35/O \*/O ,/O 54/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Building/O stone/O 86/O ./O Bulgaria/LOCATION 157/O ./O Burlington/LOCATION ,/O Iowa/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Burlington/LOCATION ,/O Vt./LOCATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Burma/LOCATION 37/O \*/O ,/O 166/O ./O Butte/O 115/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 121/O ./O C/O Cabinet/ORGANIZATION woods/O 47/O ,/O 141/O ./O Cables/O ,/O ocean/O 60/O ./O Cacao/O 44/O \*/O ,/O 141/O ./O Cactus/O 50/O \*/O ./O Cairo/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 183/O ./O Calcutta/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O California/LOCATION 11/O \*/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 119/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Callao/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Cambodia/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 172/O ./O Cambridge/LOCATION ,/O Eng/LOCATION ./O 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Cambridge/LOCATION ,/O U./ORGANIZATION S./ORGANIZATION 89/O ,/O 91/O ./O Camden/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Camel/O 54/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 165/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Canada/LOCATION 34/O ,/O 65/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 129/O ,/O 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Canals/O ,/O China/LOCATION 166/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 145/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 154/O ,/O 159/O ./O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 107/O ./O Canary/O islands/O 22/O ,/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Candia/PERSON ,/O or/O Crete/LOCATION 157/O ./O Canton/LOCATION ,/O China/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Canton/LOCATION ,/O Ohio/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Canyon/O of/O Colorado/ORGANIZATION 66/O \*/O ./O Cape/O Breton/O 131/O ./O Cape/O Cod/O 91/O ./O Cape/O Colony/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Cape/O Hatteras/O 101/O ./O Cape/O Horn/O 138/O ,/O 139/O ./O Cape/O of/O Good/O Hope/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Cape/LOCATION Town/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 180,184/O ./O Cape/O Verde/O islands/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Caracas/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Cardenas/PERSON 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Cardiff/LOCATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Caribbean/LOCATION sea/O 135/O ./O Caribou/O 52/O \*/O ,/O 56/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Caroline/PERSON islands/O 187,189/O ./O Carson/LOCATION City/LOCATION 117/O ,/O 119/O ./O Cascade/O mts/O ./O 17/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 66/O ,/O 70/O ./O Caspian/O sea/O 161/O ,/O 163/O ,/O 165/O ./O Cassava/O 141/O ,/O 181/O ./O Cassiquiari/O river/O 139/O ,/O 141/O ./O Castes/O 40/O ./O Catskills/ORGANIZATION 93/O ,/O 95/O ./O Cattle/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 54/O ,/O 80/O \*/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 159/O ,/O 181/O ,/O 188/O ./O Caucasian/LOCATION ;/O see/O White/O race/O ./O Caucasus/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 149/O ,/O 150/O ./O Cayenne/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Cedar/O Rapids/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Celebes/LOCATION 167/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 187/O ./O Centrl/LOCATION America/LOCATION 17/O ,/O 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Central/O states/O 106-109-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Cevennes/O 157/O ./O Ceylon/ORGANIZATION 38/O \*/O ,/O 169/O ./O Chamois/O 170/O \*/O ./O Chamouni/O 157/O ./O Charcoal/O 57/O \*/O ./O Charleston/LOCATION ,/O S./PERSON C./PERSON 76/O ,/O 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Charleston/LOCATION ,/O W./LOCATION Va./LOCATION 95,98/O ./O Charlotte/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Charlotte/ORGANIZATION Amalie/ORGANIZATION 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O Charlottesville/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Chattanooga/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Chautauqua/O 95/O ./O Chesapeake/LOCATION bay/O 82/O ,/O 94/O ,/O 95/O ./O Cheviot/ORGANIZATION hills/O 151/O ,/O 155/O ./O Cheyenne/ORGANIZATION 116/O ,/O 121/O ./O Chicago/LOCATION 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 108/O \*/O ,/O 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Chile/LOCATION 138/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Chimborazo/O 137/O ,/O 139/O ./O Chimpanzee/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O China/LOCATION 21/O ,/O 36/O ,/O 37/O \*/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Christiania/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Christians/O 40/O ./O Cienfuegos/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Cinchona/O ;/O see/O Peruvian/O bark/O ./O Cincinnati/LOCATION 108/O ,/O 109/O ./O Cinnamon/O 45/O ,/O 46/O \*/O ./O Circumference/O 2/O ./O Civil/O day/O 192/O ./O Cleveland/ORGANIZATION 84/O ./O Cliff/O 4/O \*/O ,/O 13/O \*/O ./O Cliff/O dwellings/O 66/O ,/O 67/O \*/O ./O Climate/O 23-32/O ./O Climate/O of/O U./ORGANIZATION S./ORGANIZATION 74/O ,/O 75/O ./O Climatic/O maps/O ,/O Heat/ORGANIZATION belts/O 27/O ,/O 28/O ./O Rainfall/O in/O U./LOCATION S./LOCATION 31/O ,/O 74/O ./O Seasons/O 25/O ,/O 75/O ./O Temperature/O in/O U./LOCATION S./LOCATION 75/O ./O Winds/O 31/O ,/O 74/O ./O Clinton/PERSON 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Cloves/O 45/O ,/O 46/O \*/O ./O Coal/O 57/O \*/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 96/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 150/O ./O Coastal/O plains/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 12/O \*/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 150/O ./O Llanos/O 140/O ./O Russia-Siberia/LOCATION 165/O ./O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 8/O \*/O ,/O 67/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 71/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 94/O ,/O 99/O \*/O ./O Coast/O range/O 17/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 66/O ,/O 70/O ./O Cochin-China/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Codfish/O 82/O \*/O ./O Coffee/O 46/O \*/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 143/O ,/O 165/O ,/O 169/O ./O Coke/ORGANIZATION 57/O \*/O ./O Colombia/LOCATION 137/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Colombo/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Colon/O 139/O ./O Colorado/ORGANIZATION 9/O \*/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 115/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O Colorado/LOCATION canyon/O 66/O \*/O ./O Colorado/LOCATION plateaus/O 9/O \*/O ,/O 66/O \*/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 118/O ./O Colorado/LOCATION river/O 66/O \*/O ,/O 70/O ./O Colorado/LOCATION Springs/LOCATION 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O Columbia/ORGANIZATION plateau/O 70/O ./O Columbia/ORGANIZATION river/O 72/O ./O Columbia/ORGANIZATION ,/O S./PERSON C./PERSON 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Columbus/LOCATION ,/O Ga./LOCATION 101,101/O ./O Columbus/LOCATION ,/O Ohio/LOCATION 109,110/O ./O Commerce/ORGANIZATION 59/O ,/O 76-87/O ;/O see/O names/O of/O sea/O ports/O ./O Compass/O 4/O \*/O ./O Concord/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Condor/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 142/O ./O Connecticut/LOCATION 88-91/O ./O Connecticut/LOCATION river/O 5/O \*/O ,/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Constantinople/ORGANIZATION 40/O \*/O ,/O 157/O ,/O 158/O \*/O ,/O 159/O ./O Consuls/O 60/O ./O Continents/O 14/O ./O Copenhagen/ORGANIZATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Copper/O 58/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 115/O ,/O 144/O ,/O 148/O ,/O 150/O ./O Cordoba/ORGANIZATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Corinth/LOCATION ,/O isthmus/O 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Corn/O 50/O \*/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 114/O ,/O 141/O ./O 181/O ,/O 186/O ,/O 188/O ./O Corsicana/O 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Costa/LOCATION Rica/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Cotopaxi/O 137/O ,/O 139/O ./O Cotton/O 48/O \*/O ,/O 76/O ,/O 99,141/O ,/O 174/O ,/O 181/O ./O Council/O Bluffs/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Covington/PERSON 109,111/O ./O Crete/LOCATION ,/O or/O Candia/O 149/O ./O Cripplecreek/O 115/O ,/O 117/O ./O Crocodile/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 171/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Cuba/LOCATION 78/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 133/O ,/O 134/O \*/O ,/O 135/O ./O Cuzco/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 143/O ./O Cypress/O swamp/O 98/O \*/O ./O D/O Dairy/O 80/O ,/O 89/O ./O Dakota/LOCATION 8/O \*/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 112/O \*/O ,/O 113/O ./O Dallas/LOCATION 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Damascus/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 173/O ./O Danube/ORGANIZATION river/O 145/O ,/O 157/O ./O Dardanelles/O 157/O ./O Date/O line/O 192/O ./O Dates/O 175/O ,/O 181/O ./O Davenport/PERSON 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Dawson/PERSON 129/O ./O Dayton/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Dead/O sea/O 163/O ,/O 164/O \*/O ./O Death/O valley/O 117/O ./O Deer/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 56/O ./O Dekkan/ORGANIZATION 21/O ,/O 161/O ,/O 166/O ,/O 167/O \*/O ./O Delaware/LOCATION 79/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 92-95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Delaware/LOCATION river/O 95/O ./O Delhi/LOCATION 167/O \*/O ,/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Delta/ORGANIZATION plains/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 12/O \*/O ./O Brahmaputra/O 167/O ,/O 17/O 3/O ./O China/LOCATION 161/O ,/O 166/O ./O Colorado/ORGANIZATION 72/O ./O Danube/ORGANIZATION 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Ganges/O 167/O ,/O 173/O ./O Indus/O 167/O ,/O 173/O ./O Mekong/ORGANIZATION 166/O ,/O 173/O ./O Mississippi/LOCATION 103/O ,/O 105/O ./O Niger/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Nile/O 177/O ,/O 179/O ./O Orinoco/O 139/O ./O Po/O 157/O ./O Rhine/O 145/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 150/O ./O Rhone/O 149/O ./O Yahtse/PERSON ,/O Alaska/ORGANIZATION 8/O \*/O ,/O 72/O ./O Yellow/O 166/O ,/O 173/O ./O Zambezi/ORGANIZATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Denmark/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Denver/LOCATION 116/O \*/O ,/O 117/O ./O Deserts/O 30/O \*/O ./O Atacama/LOCATION 19,138,139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Gobi/O 21/O ,/O 161/O ./O Kalahari/ORGANIZATION 22/O ./O Sahara/ORGANIZATION 22/O ./O Des/O Moines/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Detroit/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O INDEX/O TO/O TEXT/O AND/O MAPS/O Diameter/O 2/O ./O Diamonds/O 23/O ,/O 158/O ,/O 184/O ./O Directions/O ./O Dismal/O swamp/O 94/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 98/O \*/O ./O District/O of/O Columbia/ORGANIZATION 70/O ,/O 73/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 128/O ./O Divides/O 7/O ./O Dnieper/O river/O 149/O ./O Dover/LOCATION ,/O Del./O 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Dover/LOCATION strait/O 155/O ./O Dresden/LOCATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Drumlin/ORGANIZATION 10/O \*/O ./O Dublin/LOCATION 154/O \*/O ,/O 155/O ./O Dubuque/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Duluth/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Dundee/ORGANIZATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Dunedin/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Dunes/O 30/O \*/O ,/O 178/O \*/O ./O Durham/ORGANIZATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Dutch/LOCATION East/LOCATION Indies/LOCATION ;/O see/O East/LOCATION Indies/LOCATION ./O Dutch/O Guiana/O ,/O 139/O ./O Dwina/LOCATION river/O 149/O ./O Dyaks/O 168/O \*/O ./O Dyewoods/O 47/O ,/O 141/O ./O E/O Earth/ORGANIZATION 2/O ./O Area/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Axis/O 3/O ,/O 25/O ./O Form/O 2/O ./O Orbit/O 25/O ,/O 26/O \*/O ./O Revolves/O 25/O ,/O 26/O ./O Rotates/O 3/O ./O Size/O 2/O ./O Earthquake/O 10/O ,/O 11/O ./O East/O lndies/O 21/O ,/O 36/O \*/O ,/O 161/O ,/O 169/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 187/O ./O East/LOCATION St./LOCATION Louis/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Eau/PERSON Claire/PERSON 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Ebro/LOCATION river/O 157/O ./O Echidna/O 186/O \*/O ./O Eclipse/O 2/O ./O Ecuador/LOCATION 137/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Eddying/O storm/O 74/O ./O Edinburgh/LOCATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Egypt/LOCATION 22/O ,/O 39/O \*/O ,/O 179/O ,/O 183/O ./O Egyptian/O 183/O \*/O ./O Eider/O duck/O 130/O \*/O ,/O 132/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Eland/O 182/O \*/O ./O Elbe/ORGANIZATION river/O 157/O ./O Elephant/O 54/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 171/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Elk/O 55,170/O \*/O ./O Emu/O 186/O \*/O ./O England/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 155/O ;/O see/O also/O British/O Isles/O ./O English/O channel/O 155/O ./O Ensley/PERSON 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Equator/ORGANIZATION 3/O ,/O 14/O ,/O 25/O ./O Equatorial/O currents/O 32/O ./O Equatorial/O rains/O 31/O ./O Erie/O 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Erie/O canal/O 92/O \*/O ./O Eskimo/ORGANIZATION 17/O ,/O 37/O \*/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Essen/ORGANIZATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Euphrates/LOCATION river/O 164/O ,/O 173/O Eurasia/ORGANIZATION 14/O ,/O 21/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 19/O ,/O 20/O ./O Animals/O 170/O ./O Climate/O 152/O ./O Countries/O 153-159/O ./O People/O 153/O ./O Plants/O 152/O ./O Political/O maps/O 149/O ,/O 155/O ,/O 157/O ./O Relief/O map/O 20/O ,/O 146/O ./O Surface/O 19/O ,/O 20,145-151/O ./O Evansville/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Evaporation/O 5/O ./O Everglades/ORGANIZATION 99/O ,/O 101/O ./O F/O Falkland/O islands/O ,/O 138/O ,/O 139/O ./O Fall-line/O 93/O ,/O 94/O ,/O 99/O \*/O ./O Fall/O River/O 76/O ,/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Fargo/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Fez/O 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Fibers/O 52/O ./O Figs/O 169/O \*/O ./O Fiji/LOCATION islands/O 36/O \*/O ,/O 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Fingal/O 's/O cave/O 155/O ./O Finland/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 153/O ./O Finns/O 153/O ./O Fiord/O 12/O \*/O ,/O 19/O \*/O ,/O 150/O ./O Fire/O temple/O 40/O \*/O ./O Firth/O of/O Clyde/PERSON 155/O ./O Firth/O of/O Forth/O 155/O ./O Fisheries/O 81/O ,/O 82/O \*/O ./O Flax/O 51/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 158/O ,/O 159/O ./O Flood/O plains/O 8/O \*/O ./O Amazon/O 140/O ./O Brahmaputra/O 167/O ./O Ganges/O 167/O ./O Indus/O 167/O ./O Mississippi/LOCATION 78/O \*/O ,/O 99,103/O ,/O 105/O ./O Nile/ORGANIZATION 177/O ,/O 181/O ./O Orinoco/O 141/O ./O Rhine/O 150/O \*/O ./O Florence/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Florida/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 101/O ./O Fog/O 11/O ./O Forests/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 18/O \*/O ,/O 19/O ,/O 23/O ,/O 49/O \*/O ,/O 51/O \*/O ,/O 52/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 99/O \*/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 165/O ./O Form/O of/O earth/O 2/O ./O Formosa/O 173/O ./O Fort/O Smith/PERSON 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Fort/O Wayne/PERSON 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Forth/O Worth/O 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Fossil/O shell/O 16/O ./O France/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 150/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Frankfort/O 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Frankfurt/LOCATION 156/O \*/O ,/O 157/O ./O Fraser/PERSON river/O 131/O ./O Freetown/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O French/O Guiana/O 139/O ./O French/LOCATION Indo-China/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Friendly/O islands/O ;/O see/O Tonga/LOCATION ./O Frigid/O zones/O 24/O \*/O ,/O 27/O ,/O 28/O ,/O 51/O ,/O 52/O \*/O ./O Fruit/O 79/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 152/O ./O Fuchau/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Fujiyama/O 167/O \*/O ,/O 173/O ./O Furniture/O 79/O ./O Fur/O seals/O 122/O ./O G/O Galapagos/O islands/O 139/O ./O Galveston/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 103,104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Ganges/O 166/O ,/O 173/O ./O Garonne/O river/O 157/O ./O Gavial/O 55/O \*/O ./O Geneva/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Genoa/ORGANIZATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Georgetown/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Georgia/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 98/O -/O 101/O ./O Geral/O mts/O ./O 139/O ./O Germany/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 150/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Geyser/O 6/O \*/O ,/O 115/O ./O Ghats/O ,/O Western/O 173/O ./O Giant/O 's/O causeway/O 151/O ,/O 155/O ./O Gibraltar/LOCATION 148/O ,/O 149/O ./O Gila/LOCATION river/O 72/O ./O Gilbert/PERSON islands/O 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Ginger/O 46/O ./O Giraffe/O 182/O \*/O ./O Gironde/ORGANIZATION river/O 157/O ./O Glacial/O lakes/O 10/O \*/O ./O Glacier/O 10/O \*/O ./O Glasgow/LOCATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Glass/O 58/O ,/O 59/O \*/O ,/O 97,156/O ,/O 158/O ./O Globe/O maps/O ,/O Africa/LOCATION 22/O ./O America/LOCATION 2/O ./O Asia/LOCATION 21/O ./O Australia/LOCATION 23/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 20/O ./O Heat/O belts/O 28/O ./O North/LOCATION America/LOCATION 17/O ./O Oceans/O 16/O ./O South/LOCATION America/LOCATION 19/O ./O Zones/O 25/O ,/O 27/O ,/O 28/O ./O Gloucester/ORGANIZATION 82/O ./O Gnu/O 182/O \*/O ./O Gobi/O desert/O 21/O ,/O 161/O ./O God/O 39/O ./O Gold/O 23/O ,/O 58/O \*/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 115/O ,/O 118/O ,/O 119/O ,/O 122/O ,/O 185/O ,/O 188/O ,/O 189/O ./O Gold/O coast/O 22/O ./O Golden/O Gate/O 117/O ,/O 120/O ./O Gorilla/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Gottenborg/O 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Government/O of/O U.S./LOCATION 128/O ./O Governments/O 40/O ,/O 41/O ./O Grain/O ;/O see/O Wheat/O ,/O Corn/ORGANIZATION ,/O etc./O ./O Grampian/LOCATION hills/O 155/O ./O Granada/ORGANIZATION 148/O ,/O 149/O ./O Grand/O Manan/O 95/O ./O Grand/O Rapids/O 79/O ,/O 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Granite/O 58/O ,/O 59/O \*/O ,/O 89/O ,/O 100/O ./O Grapes/O 49/O \*/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 152/O ./O Grass/O 51/O ./O Great/O Basin/O 17/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 66/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 85/O ./O Great/LOCATION Britain/LOCATION 121/O ;/O see/O British/O Isles/O ./O Great/O Falls/O 116/O ./O Great/LOCATION Lakes/LOCATION l7/LOCATION ,/O 70,107/O ./O Great/O Salt/O lake/O 65/O ,/O 66/O ./O Great/O wall/O 21/O ./O Greater/O Antilles/O 135/O ./O Greece/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Greenland/LOCATION 10/O \*/O ,/O 65/O ,/O 132/O ./O Green/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 67/O ,/O 88/O ,/O 89/O \*/O ,/O 91/O ./O Greenville/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Greenwich/LOCATION 155/O ./O Ground/O water/O 5/O ./O Guadalquivir/O river/O 149/O ./O Guam/LOCATION 125/O ,/O 127/O ./O Guatemala/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Guayaquil/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Guiana/LOCATION 139,140/O ,/O 143/O ,/O 144/O ./O Guinea/LOCATION 22/O ./O Gulf/O 12/O ./O Gulf/O coastal/O plain/O ,/O or/O Southern/O plain/O ;/O see/O Coastal/ORGANIZATION plains/O ./O Gulf/O of/O Bothnia/LOCATION 149/O ./O Gulf/O of/O California/LOCATION 131/O ./O Gulf/O of/O Finland/LOCATION 149/O ./O Gulf/O of/O Guayaqui1/O 139/O ./O Gulf/O of/O Guinea/LOCATION 179/O ./O Gulf/O of/O Mexico/ORGANIZATION 65/O ./O Gulf/O of/O St./ORGANIZATION Lawrence/ORGANIZATION 65/O ./O Gulf/O stream/O 32/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 152/O ./O Guthrie/PERSON 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O H/O Haiti/LOCATION 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Hakodate/LOCATION 173/O ./O Halifax/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Hamburg/LOCATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Hamilton/LOCATION 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Hanoi/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Harbors/O 12/O ,/O 13/O ,/O 60/O ./O Harrisburg/LOCATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Hartford/ORGANIZATION 91/O ,/O 92/O ./O Hastings/O 113/O ./O Havana/LOCATION 132/O \*/O ,/O 134/O \*/O ,/O 135/O ./O Haverhill/ORGANIZATION 91/O ./O Havre/PERSON 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Hawaii/LOCATION 36/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 123/O ,/O 124/O \*/O ./O Heat/O belts/O 28/O ,/O 29/O \*/O ./O Hebrides/O 155/O ./O Helena/PERSON 116/O ,/O 121/O ./O Hemispheres/O 3/O ,/O 4/O ,/O 14/O ./O Hemp/O 51/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 124/O ,/O 169/O ./O Hemp/O ,/O Sisal/O 132/O ./O Herat/LOCATION 173/O ./O Hides/O ;/O see/O Cattle/O ./O Highlander/O 153/O ./O Highways/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Trade/ORGANIZATION 59/O ,/O 60/O ./O Hills/ORGANIZATION 5/O \*/O ,/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 9/O ,/O 10/O \*/O ./O Hilo/LOCATION 123/O ,/O 124/O ./O Himalaya/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 20/O \*/O ,/O 161/O ,/O 173/O ./O Hindu/ORGANIZATION Kush/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 173/O ./O Hindus/O 38/O \*/O ,/O 39/O ,/O 172/O ./O Hindustan/O 166/O ,/O 173/O ./O Hippopotamus/O 182/O \*/O ./O Hoangho/LOCATION ;/O see/O Yellow/O river/O ./O Hobart/O 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Hoboken/ORGANIZATION 95/O ./O Hogs/O 54/O ,/O 81/O ./O Holland/ORGANIZATION 149/O ,/O 150/O \*/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Holyoke/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Honduras/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Hongkong/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Honolulu/LOCATION 120/O ,/O 123/O ,/O 124/O \*/O ./O Horizon/ORGANIZATION 2/O \*/O ./O Horses/O 54/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 165/O ./O Hot/O spring/O 6/O ./O Hot/O Springs/LOCATION 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Houston/LOCATION 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Hudson/LOCATION bay/O 65/O ./O Hudson/LOCATION river/O 67/O ,/O 72/O ,/O 92/O \*/O ./O Hue/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Hugli/PERSON river/O 173/O ./O Humboldt/LOCATION river/O 72/O ./O Hungary/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 159/O ./O Huntington/O 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Huntsville/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Hydraulic/O mining/O 58/O \*/O ,/O 119/O ./O Hyena/O 182/O \*/O ./O I/O Ibex/O 170/O \*/O ./O Iceberg/ORGANIZATION 10/O \*/O ,/O 11/O ./O Ice/O floe/O 10/O \*/O ./O Iceland/LOCATION 132/O ,/O 149/O ./O 11/O ./O Ice/O sheet/O 10/O \*/O ,/O 88/O ./O Idaho/ORGANIZATION 11/O \*/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 118/O ,/O 119/O ,/O 121/O ./O Iguana/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ./O Illinois/ORGANIZATION 83/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 106-109/O ./O Iloilo/O 125/O ,/O 127/O ./O Incas/ORGANIZATION 143/O ./O India/ORGANIZATION 21/O ,/O 38/O \*/O ,/O 76/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Indiana/ORGANIZATION 84/O ,/O 106-109/O ./O Indianapolis/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Indian/O ocean/O 16/O ./O Indians/ORGANIZATION ;/O see/O Red/O race/O ./O Indian/O Territory/O 83/O ,/O 103/O ,/O 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O India/LOCATION rubber/O 47/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 143/O ./O Indigo/O 169/O ,/O 174/O ./O Indo-China/LOCATION 21/O ,/O 166/O ,/O 172/O ,/O Indus/ORGANIZATION river/O 173/O ./O International/O date/O line/O 192/O ./O Iowa/LOCATION 111-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Iquique/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Iran/LOCATION plateau/O 21/O ,/O 161/O ,/O 164/O ./O Ireland/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 155/O ;/O see/O also/O British/O Isles/O ./O Irkutsk/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Iron/O 17/O \*/O ,/O 56/O \*/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 150/O ./O Iron/O gate/O 145/O ./O Irrigation/O in/O Asia/LOCATION 164/O ,/O 168/O ./O Euphrates/O 164/O ./O Great/LOCATION Basin/LOCATION 116/O ,/O 118/O ./O Iran/LOCATION 164/O ./O Nile/ORGANIZATION valley/O 177/O ./O Northern/O Africa/O 178/O ./O Spain/LOCATION 148/O ./O Temperate/O zone/O 50/O ./O Western/O plains/O 71/O \*/O ,/O 112/O ,/O 115/O \*/O ./O Isla/ORGANIZATION de/ORGANIZATION Pinos/ORGANIZATION 133/O ,/O 135/O ./O Island/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 11/O ./O Isthmus/O 12/O \*/O ./O Italy/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Itasca/LOCATION lake/O 113/O ./O Ithaca/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O Ivory/O 165/O ,/O 183/O ,/O 184/O ./O Ivory/O coast/O 22/O ./O J/PERSON Jackson/PERSON ,/O Mich./LOCATION 109/O ./O Jackson/LOCATION ,/O Miss./LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Jacksonville/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Jaguar/ORGANIZATION 54/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ./O Jamaica/LOCATION 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O James/PERSON river/O 95/O ./O Japan/LOCATION 21/O ,/O 36/O ,/O 37/O \*/O ,/O 167/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Japan/LOCATION current/O 122/O ./O Java/O 36/O \*/O ,/O 167/O ,/O 168/O \*/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 187/O ./O Jefferson/LOCATION City/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Jersey/ORGANIZATION City/ORGANIZATION 95/ORGANIZATION ,/O 96/O ,/O 97/O ./O Jerusalem/LOCATION 39/O \*/O ,/O 163,165/O ,/O 175/O ./O Jetties/O 111/O \*/O ./O Jewelry/O 90/O ./O Jewish/O people/O 40/O ./O Johannesburg/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Joliet/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Joplin/PERSON 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Jordan/LOCATION river/O 163/O ,/O 164/O ./O Juneau/PERSON 122/O ,/O 123/O ./O Jura/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Jute/O 169/O ,/O 174/O ./O K/O Kabul/ORGANIZATION 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Kadiak/O 123/O ./O Great/LOCATION Valley/LOCATION 70/O ./O I/O Kaffirs/ORGANIZATION 33/O \*/O ,/O 181/O \*/O ,/O 183/O ./O Kalahari/ORGANIZATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ,/O 181/O ./O Kamchatka/ORGANIZATION 173/O ./O Kamerun/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Kangaroo/O 54/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ./O Kansas/LOCATION 111-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Kansas/ORGANIZATION City/ORGANIZATION 80/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 112/O ,/O 173/O ./O Karakoram/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 161/O ./O Karpathian/O mts/O ./O 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Kashmir/LOCATION 162/O \*/O ,/O 173/O ./O Keewatin/O 131/O ./O Kenia/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Kentucky/LOCATION 106-109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Kerosene/O ;/O see/O Petroleum/O ./O Key/O West/O 78/O ,/O 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Khaibar/O pass/O 164/O \*/O ./O Khelat/O 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Khiva/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Kilauea/O 123/O ./O Kilimanjaro/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Killarney/ORGANIZATION 7/O \*/O ,/O 155/O ./O Kimberley/O 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Kingston/ORGANIZATION 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Klondike/ORGANIZATION 85/O ./O Knoxville/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Koala/O 186/O \*/O ./O Kobe/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Kong/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 22/O ,/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Kongo/LOCATION river/O 23/O ,/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Kongo/LOCATION State/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Korea/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Kuenlun/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 173/O ./O Kuka/LOCATION 179/O ./O Kyoto/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O L/O Labrador/ORGANIZATION 17/O ,/O 129/O ,/O 131/O ./O Lachine/LOCATION rapids/O 7/O \*/O ./O La/ORGANIZATION Crosse/ORGANIZATION 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Ladrone/O islands/O 125/O ,/O 127/O ./O Lagoon/O 13/O \*/O ./O Lake/O plains/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 9/O ,/O 167/O \*/O ./O Caspian/O 161/O ,/O 165/O ./O Hungary/LOCATION 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Kashmir/LOCATION 162/O \*/O ,/O 173/O ./O Prairies/O 106/O ./O Red/O river/O 77/O ,/O 106/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 130/O ./O Lakes/O 6/O ,/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 10/O \*/O ,/O 11/O \*/O ,/O 17/O \*/O ,/O 88/O ,/O 94/O ./O Baikal/ORGANIZATION 163/O ,/O 165/O ./O Champlain/O 88/O \*/O ,/O 92/O ,/O 95/O ./O Como/O 145/O ,/O 147/O ./O Erie/O 73/O ./O Garda/O 145/O ,/O 147/O ./O Geneva/LOCATION 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O George/PERSON 92/O ,/O 95/O ./O Huron/ORGANIZATION 73/O ./O Killarney/ORGANIZATION 7/O \*/O ./O Ladoga/O 149/O ./O Lucerne/LOCATION 148/O :/O Maggiore/ORGANIZATION 145/O ,/O 147/O ./O Michigan/LOCATION 73/O ./O Nicaragua/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Ontario/ORGANIZATION 73/O ./O Superior/O 73/O ./O Tanganyika/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Tchad/O 178/O ,/O 1790/O ./O Titicaca/ORGANIZATION 18/O ,/O 34/O ./O Victoria/O 179/O ./O Wenner/PERSON 149/O ./O Lansing/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O La/PERSON Paz/PERSON 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Lapland/LOCATION 37/O \*/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 153/O ./O La/ORGANIZATION Plata/ORGANIZATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Lapps/O 153/O ./O Laramie/ORGANIZATION 70/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 121/O ./O Lassa/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Latitude/O 23/O ,/O 24/O ./O Lava/O plains/O 11/O \*/O ,/O 118/O \*/O ,/O 124/O \*/O ./O Columbia/ORGANIZATION plateau/O 70/O ,/O 118/O \*/O ./O Dekkan/O 161/O ,/O 167/O \*/O ./O Lawrence/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Lead/O 85/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 114/O ,/O 148/O ,/O 150/O ./O Lead/O City/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Leadville/ORGANIZATION 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O Leather/O 80/O ,/O 97/O ./O Leavenworth/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Leeward/O islands/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Leipzig/LOCATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Lemur/O 182/O \*/O ./O Lena/PERSON river/O 163/O ./O Lengths/O of/O rivers/O ;/O Sup/O ./O Leon/PERSON 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Leopard/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Lesser/O Antilles/O 135/O ./O Lewiston/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Lexington/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Liberia/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Lichens/O 51/O ,/O 52/O \*/O ./O Liege/O 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Lighthouses/O 60/O ./O Lima/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O \*/O ./O Lime/O and/O limestone/O 58/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 93/O ./O Lincoln/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Linen/O 51/O ./O Lion/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Lisbon/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Lisle/ORGANIZATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Little/O Rock/O 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Liverpool/ORGANIZATION 153/O ,/O 154/O ,/O 155/O Llama/ORGANIZATION 54/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ./O Llanos/ORGANIZATION 19/O ,/O 137/O ,/O 140/O \*/O ,/O 141/O ./O Lochs/O 155/O ./O Locomotives/O 90/O ,/O 97/O ./O Loire/ORGANIZATION 157/O ./O London/LOCATION 41/O \*/O ,/O 153/O \*/O ,/O 154/O \*/O ,/O 155/O ./O Long/LOCATION Island/LOCATION 95/O ./O Longitude/O 23/O ,/O 24/O ./O Longs/O peak/O 65/O ,/O 66/O ./O Los/O Angeles/O 117/O ,/O 120/O ./O Louisiana/LOCATION 85/O ,/O 103/O ,/O 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Louisville/LOCATION 78/O ,/O 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Lowe11/O 76/O ,/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Lower/LOCATION California/LOCATION 131/O ./O Lumber/O ;/O see/O Forests/O ./O Luray/ORGANIZATION 93/O \*/O ,/O 95/O ./O Luzon/LOCATION 124/O ,/O 127/O ./O Lynchburg/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Lynn/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Lyon/ORGANIZATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Lyre/O bird/O 186/O \*/O ./O M/O Mackenzie/PERSON river/O 131/O ./O Mackerel/O 82/O ./O Macon/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Madagascar/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Madeira/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Madison/O 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Madras/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Madrid/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Magdalena/PERSON river/O 137/O ,/O 139/O ./O Magellan/O strait/O 138/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 140/O ./O Magnetic/O pole/O 65/O ./O Mahogany/O 133/O ./O Mails/O 60/O ./O Maine/LOCATION 51/O \*/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 88-91/O ./O Malaga/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Malay/O Archipelago/O ;/O see/O East/LOCATION Indies/LOCATION ./O Malay/O peninsula/O 21/O ./O Malay/O race/O ;/O see/O Brown/PERSON race/O ./O Mammoth/O cave/O 93/O ,/O 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Managua/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Manchester/LOCATION ,/O N./PERSON H./PERSON 88/O \*/O ,/O 91/O ./O Manchester/LOCATION ,/O Eng/LOCATION ./O 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Manchester/LOCATION canal/O 154/O ./O Manchuria/LOCATION 173/O ./O Mandalay/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Manhattan/ORGANIZATION 96/O ./O Manila/LOCATION 124/O \*/O ,/O 125/O ,/O 127/O ./O Manitoba/LOCATION 129/O ,/O 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Manna/O 126/O ,/O 187/O ./O Manufacturing/O 76-87/O ;/O see/O also/O names/O of/O cities/O ./O Map/O drawing/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Maps/O ;/O see/O Climatic/ORGANIZATION ,/O Globe/ORGANIZATION ,/O Political/O ,/O Production/O ,/O Relief/O ./O Marathon/O 157/O ./O Marble/O 58/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 89/O ./O Mariner/O 's/O compass/O 4/O \*/O ./O Marseille/ORGANIZATION 156/O ,/O 157,158/O \*/O ./O Marshall/PERSON islands/O 187,189/O ./O Marshes/O 13/O \*/O ./O Marthas/ORGANIZATION Vineyard/ORGANIZATION 91/O ./O Maryland/ORGANIZATION 9/O \*/O ,/O 92-95/O 97/O ./O Maskat/O 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Massachusetts/ORGANIZATION 80/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 88/O \*/O -/O 91/O ./O Matanzas/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Mauna/O Loa/O 123/O ./O Mediterranean/LOCATION sea/O 155/O ./O Mekka/ORGANIZATION 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Mekong/ORGANIZATION river/O 166/O ,/O 173/O ./O Melbourne/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 188/O ./O Memphis/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Meriden/ORGANIZATION 91/O ,/O 92/O ./O Meridian/O 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Meridian/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Greenwich/ORGANIZATION 24/O ,/O 155/O ./O Meridians/O 24/O ./O Merrimac/ORGANIZATION river/O 88/O ,/O 91/O ./O Mersey/O river/O 155/O ./O Mexico/LOCATION ,/O city/O 65/O ,/O 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Mexico/LOCATION ,/O country/O 34/O ,/O 38/O \*/O ,/O 65/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ,/O 133/O \*/O ./O Michigan/LOCATION 79/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 106-109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Micronesia/LOCATION 187/O ./O Middle/LOCATION Atlantic/LOCATION states/O 92-95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Middle/LOCATION basin/O 21/O ,/O 162/O ./O Milan/ORGANIZATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Military/O academy/O 96/O ./O Millet/O 169/O ./O Millinery/O 156/O ./O Milwaukee/ORGANIZATION 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Mindanao/LOCATION 124/O ,/O 127/O ./O Minerals/O 56/O ./O Mines/O 56/O \*/O ./O Minneapolis/ORGANIZATION 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Minnehaha/O falls/O 113/O ./O Minnesota/LOCATION 77/O ,/O 111-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Mississippi/LOCATION 98/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Mississippi/LOCATION river/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 111/O ./O Missouri/O 111/O ,/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Mobile/O 102/O ,/O 105/O ./O Mocha/O 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Modeling/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Mohammed/O 175/O ./O Mohave/LOCATION desert/O 117/O ./O Mohawk/O valley/O 67/O ,/O 73/O ,/O 92/O \*/O ./O Molokai/LOCATION 123/O ./O Monaco/ORGANIZATION 145/O \*/O ,/O 149/O ./O Monarchy/O 40/O ,/O 41/O ./O Mongolia/LOCATION 173/O ./O Mongolian/LOCATION ;/O see/O Yellow/O race/O ./O Monkey/ORGANIZATION 54/O \*/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ,/O 171/O \*/O ./O Monrovia/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Monsoons/O 168/O ./O Montana/LOCATION 85/O ,/O 115/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 121/O ./O Mont/ORGANIZATION Blanc/ORGANIZATION 157/O ./O Mont/O Cenis/O 145/O ,/O 147/O ./O Montenegro/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Montevideo/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Montgomery/O 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Montpelier/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Montreal/LOCATION 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Moon/ORGANIZATION 2/O ,/O 12/O ,/O Moors/ORGANIZATION 148/O ./O Moose/O 67/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Morocco/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Moscow/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Mosses/O 51/O ,/O 52/O \*/O ./O Mountains/O 9/O \*/O ,/O 10/O \*/O ,/O 11/O \*/O ,/O 19/O \*/O ,/O 20/O \*/O ,/O 145/O \*/O ./O Ararat/O 163/O ,/O 164/O ./O Blanc/O 157/O ./O Elburz/O 149/O ,/O 150/O ./O Etna/O 147/O ,/O 149/O ./O Everest/O 173/O ./O Heights/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Hekla/ORGANIZATION 132/O ,/O 149/O ./O Flood/O 66/O ,/O 72/O ./O Kenia/O 179/O ./O Kilimanjaro/O 179/O ./O Logan/ORGANIZATION 72/O ,/O 122/O ,/O 123/O ./O Mansfield/ORGANIZATION 89/O \*/O ,/O 91/O ./O McKinley/PERSON 122/O ,/O 123/O ./O Mitchell/PERSON 67/O ,/O 73/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 101/O ./O Rainier/ORGANIZATION 66/O ,/O 72/O ./O Shasta/ORGANIZATION 66/O ,/O 72/O ,/O 118/O \*/O ./O St./O Elias/O 122/O ,/O 123/O ./O Washington/LOCATION 67/O \*/O ,/O 73/O ,/O 88/O ./O Whitney/ORGANIZATION 66/O ,/O 72/O ./O Mulberry/O 152/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 169/O ./O Munich/LOCATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Murray/PERSON river/O 185/O ,/O 187/O ./O Muscogee/O 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Muskegon/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O N/O Nanling/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 173/O ./O Nantucket/ORGANIZATION 91/O ./O Naples/LOCATION 147/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Narragansett/O bay/O 91/O ./O Nashville/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Nassau/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Natchez/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Natural/O bridge/O 93/O \*/O ,/O 95/O ./O Natural/O gas/O 57/O ,/O 93/O ./O Naval/O academy/O 98/O ./O Navy/ORGANIZATION yards/O 90/O ,/O 96/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 102/O ,/O 120/O ./O Nebraska/LOCATION 111-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Negritos/ORGANIZATION 125/O \*/O ./O Negro/O race/O ;/O see/O Black/PERSON race/O ./O Negro/O river/O 131/O ./O Nelson/PERSON river/O 151/O ./O Netherlands/LOCATION ;/O see/O Holland/ORGANIZATION ./O Nevada/LOCATION 85/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 117,119/O ./O New/LOCATION Albany/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Newark/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O New/O Brunswick/O 129/O ,/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O New/O England/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 88/O \*/O -/O 90/O ./O Newfoundland/LOCATION 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Banks/O 82/O ./O New/LOCATION Guatemala/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O New/LOCATION Guinea/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O New/O Hampshire/ORGANIZATION 88/O ,/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O New/O Haven/O 88/O \*/O ,/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O New/ORGANIZATION Jersey/ORGANIZATION 8/O \*/O ,/O 92-95/O ,/O 97/O ./O New/LOCATION Mexico/LOCATION 115/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O New/O Orleans/O 76/O ,/O 104/O \*/O ,/O 105/O ./O Newport/LOCATION ,/O R.I./LOCATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Newport/LOCATION ,/O Ky./LOCATION 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O New/LOCATION South/LOCATION Wales/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 188/O ./O New/LOCATION York/LOCATION city/O 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 92/O \*/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 96/O \*/O ./O New/LOCATION York/LOCATION state/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 92/O \*/O -95/O ,/O 96/O ./O New/LOCATION Zealand/LOCATION 36/O \*/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Niagara/ORGANIZATION 94/O \*/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O Nicaragua/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Nicaragua/LOCATION canal/O 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Niger/LOCATION river/O 178/O ,/O 179/O ./O Nile/ORGANIZATION 22/O ,/O 76/O ,/O 175/O ,/O 177/O ,/O 179/O ,/O 181/O ./O Niter/O 122/O ,/O 123/O ,/O 144/O ./O Norfolk/LOCATION 76/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O North/LOCATION America/LOCATION 17/O ,/O 18/O ,/O 62/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 65/O ./O North/O cape/O 149/O ,/O 150/O ./O North/LOCATION Carolina/LOCATION 79/O ,/O 98-101/O ./O North/LOCATION Dakota/LOCATION 77/O ,/O 111-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Northern/O lights/O 28/O ./O Northern/O plain/O 17/O ,/O 20/O ./O Norway/LOCATION 19/O ,/O 148/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 150/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 159/O ./O Nova/LOCATION Scotia/LOCATION 129/O ,/O 131/O ./O Nubia/O 179/O ./O Nutmegs/O 45/O ,/O 46/O \*/O ./O 0/O Oahu/ORGANIZATION 123/O ./O Oakland/ORGANIZATION 117/O ,/O 120/O ./O Oasis/ORGANIZATION 22/O ,/O 178/O \*/O ./O Oats/O 78/O ./O Ob/O river/O 163/O ./O Ocean/LOCATION currents/O 32/O ./O Ocean/LOCATION routes/O 190-191/O ./O Oceans/O 14/O ,/O 15/O ,/O 16/O ,/O 30/O \*/O ./O Oder/O river/O 157/O ./O Odessa/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Ogden/PERSON 117/O ,/O 118/O ./O Ohio/LOCATION 83/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 106-109/O ./O Ohio/LOCATION river/O 109/O ./O Oil/O ;/O see/O Petroleum/O ./O Okhotsk/LOCATION sea/O 163/O ./O Oklahoma/LOCATION 103-105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Old/O World/O 45/O \*/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ./O Olympia/O 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Omaha/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Oman/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Ontario/LOCATION 129/O ,/O 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Opium/O poppy/O 169/O ,/O 174/O ./O Oporto/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Opossum/ORGANIZATION 87/O ./O Orange/O river/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ,/O 181/O ./O Oranges/O 49/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 119/O \*/O ./O Orang-outang/O 171/O \*/O ./O Orbit/O 25/O ,/O 26/O \*/O ./O Orchard/O fruits/O 79/O ,/O 80/O ./O Oregon/LOCATION 9/O \*/O ,/O 119/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Ores/O 56/O ./O Orinoco/O river/O colony/O 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Orizaba/ORGANIZATION 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Orkney/LOCATION islands/O 155/O ./O Ornithorhynchus/O 186/O \*/O ./O Osaka/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Oshkosh/O 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Ostrich/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ,/O 184/O ./O Ottawa/LOCATION 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Ottoman/O empire/O 159/O ./O Oxford/ORGANIZATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Oyster/O 81/O ,/O 82/O ./O Ozark/O highland/O 70/O ./O P/O Pacific/LOCATION islands/O 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O 190/O ./O Pacific/LOCATION ocean/O 16/O ./O Paducah/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Pagans/O 40/O ,/O 41/O ./O Pago/O Pago/O 126/O ,/O 187/O ./O Palm/LOCATION oil/O 44/O ,/O 181/O ./O Palms/O 44/O \*/O ,/O 181/O ./O Pamir/ORGANIZATION 21/O ,/O 161/O ,/O 162/O ./O Pampas/O 19/O ,/O 137/O ,/O 140/O ./O Panama/ORGANIZATION 14/O ,/O 137/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Papua/LOCATION ;/O see/O New/LOCATION Guinea/LOCATION ./O Para/O 139/O ,/O 143/O ./O Paraguay/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Paraguay/LOCATION river/O 139/O ./O Parallels/O 23/O ./O Paramaribo/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Parana/LOCATION river/O 139/O ./O Paris/LOCATION 156/O \*/O ,/O 157/O ./O Parkersburg/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Parrot/O 142/O ./O Parsee/ORGANIZATION 38/O \*/O ./O Patagonia/LOCATION 19,139,140/O \*/O ./O Paterson/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Pantucket/O 88/O \*/O ,/O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Peaches/O 49/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 99/O ./O Peanuts/O 94/O ./O Peat/O 151/O ./O Peccary/ORGANIZATION 87/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ./O Pekin/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Peninsula/O 12/O \*/O ./O Pennsylvania/LOCATION 83/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 92-95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Penobscot/O river/O 88/O ,/O 91/O ./O Pensacola/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O People/O 33-38/O ./O Africa/LOCATION 182/O ./O Asia/LOCATION 171/O ./O Australia/LOCATION 188/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 153/O ./O North/ORGANIZATION America/ORGANIZATION 61/ORGANIZATION ,/O 63/O ,/O 64/O ,/O 130/O ,/O 132/O ,/O 133/O ./O South/LOCATION America/LOCATION 142/O ./O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 61/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 64/O ./O Peoria/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Pepper/O 46/O \*/O ,/O 141/O ./O Pernambuco/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 143/O \*/O ./O Persia/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 164/O ,/O 175/O ./O Persian/LOCATION gulf/O 163/O ./O Peru/LOCATION 138/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Peruvian/O bark/O 138/O \*/O ./O Petersburg/ORGANIZATION 93/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Petroleum/O 57/O \*/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 96/O \*/O ,/O 103/O ,/O 150/O ./O Philadelphia/ORGANIZATION 80/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 84/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 96/O ,/O 97/O ./O Philippine/O islands/O 35/O \*/O ,/O 124/O ,/O 125/O \*/O ,/O 127/O ,/O 173/O ./O Phnix/O 117/O ,/O 119/O ./O Phosphate/O 100/O ./O Piedmont/O 70/O ,/O 92/O ,/O 94/O ./O Pierre/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Pikes/O peak/O 65/O ,/O 66/O ./O Pindus/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 157/O ./O Pine/O Bluff/O 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Pisa/LOCATION 157/O ./O Pittsburg/ORGANIZATION 83/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Plain/O of/O China/LOCATION 161/O ,/O 166/O ./O Plain/O of/O Hungary/LOCATION 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Plains/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 18/O \*/O ./O Planets/O 2/O ./O Plant/O belts/O 42/O \*/O -52/O \*/O ./O Plata/LOCATION river/O 139/O ./O Plata/PERSON valley/O 139/O ,/O 140/O ./O Plateaus/O 9/O \*/O ./O Abyssinia/ORGANIZATION 22/O ./O Bolivia/ORGANIZATION 19/O ./O Iran/ORGANIZATION 21/O ./O Mexico/LOCATION 17/O ./O Tibet/ORGANIZATION 21/O ./O Plymouth/ORGANIZATION 89/O ,/O 91/O ./O Pnum/PERSON Penh/PERSON 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Po/O 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Pocatello/LOCATION 119/O ,/O 121/O ./O Pole/O ,/O magnetic/O 65/O ./O Poles/O 3/O ./O Political/O maps/O ,/O Africa/LOCATION 179/O ./O Alaska/LOCATION 123/O ./O Asia/LOCATION 163/O ./O Australia/LOCATION 187/O ./O British/O Isles/O 155/O ./O Canada/LOCATION 131/O ./O Central/LOCATION America/LOCATION 131/O ./O Central/O Europe/LOCATION 157/O ./O Central/O states/O 109/O ,/O 113/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 149/O ./O Mexico/LOCATION 131/O ./O Middle/LOCATION states/O 95/O ./O New/LOCATION England/LOCATION 91/O ./O North/LOCATION America/LOCATION 65/O ./O Northwestern/O states/O 121/O ./O Palestine/LOCATION 163/O ./O South/LOCATION America/LOCATION 139/O ./O Southeast/LOCATION Asia/LOCATION 173/O ./O Southern/O states/O 101/O ,/O 105/O ./O Southwestern/O states/O 117/O ./O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 72-73/O ./O West/LOCATION Indies/LOCATION 135/O ./O World/O ,/O commerce/O 190-191/O ./O Pompeii/LOCATION 147/O \*/O ,/O 149/O ./O Ponce/O 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O Popocatepetl/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Population/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Porcelain/O 156/O ./O Pork/LOCATION ;/O see/O Hogs/O ./O Port/O au/O Prince/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Portland/LOCATION ,/O Me/O ./O 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Portland/LOCATION ,/O Ore./LOCATION 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Porto/ORGANIZATION Rico/ORGANIZATION 85/O ,/O 126/O ,/O 134/O \*/O ,/O 135/O ./O Port/O Said/O 175/O ,/O 179/O ./O Portsmouth/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Portugal/LOCATION 143/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Potomac/LOCATION river/O 90/O ./O Potosi/PERSON 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Prairies/O 17/O ,/O 18/O ,/O 50/O \*/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 71/O \*/O ,/O 106/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 111/O ./O Pretoria/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Pribilof/O islands/O 122/O ,/O 123/O ./O Primary/O highland/O 15/O ./O Prince/O Edward/PERSON island/O 129/O ,/O 131/O ./O Production/O maps/O ,/O Cattle/ORGANIZATION 80/O ./O Coal/O 83/O ./O Copper/O 85/O ./O Corn/O 77/O ./O Cotton/O 76/O ./O Dairying/O 80/O ./O Fisheries/O 82/O ./O Forests/O 79/O ./O Gold/O 85/O ./O Hogs/O 81/O ./O Iron/O 83/O ./O Iron/O manuf/O ./O 84/O ./O Petroleum/O 84/O ./O Sheep/O 81/O ./O Silver/O 85/O ./O Tobacco/O 78/O ./O Wheat/O 77/O ./O Wool/O 81/O ./O Zinc/O 85/O ./O Pronouncing/O Vocabulary/O ;/O Sup/O ./O vi-viii/O ./O Providence/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Pueblo/O 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O Puerto/O Principe/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Puget/O sound/O 119/O ,/O 121/O ./O Puma/ORGANIZATION 54/O \*/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Puno/LOCATION 138/O \*/O ,/O 139/O ./O Pyramid/O 177/O \*/O ,/O 179/O ./O Pyrenees/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 147/O ,/O 149/O ./O Q/O Quagga/O 182/O \*/O ./O Quarry/O 56/O ./O Quebec/LOCATION 129/O ,/O 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Queensland/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Quincy/O ,/O Ill./LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Quinine/O ;/O see/O Peruvian/O bark/O ./O Quito/LOCATION 137/O ,/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O vii/O ./O R/O Races/O of/O men/O 33/O \*/O ,/O 34/O \*/O ,/O 35/O \*/O ,/O 36/O \*/O ,/O 37/O \*/O ,/O 38/O \*/O ./O Racine/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Railroads/O 1/O \*/O ,/O 60/O \*/O ./O Time/O belts/O 193/O ./O Rainfall/O 5/O \*/O ,/O 29/O ,/O 30/O ,/O 31/O ./O Raised/O maps/O ;/O see/O Relief/O ./O Raisins/O 80/O ,/O 152/O ./O Raleigh/ORGANIZATION 99/O ,/O 101/O ./O Rangoon/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ,/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Rapids/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 99/O \*/O ./O Rattan/O 44/O ./O Reading/O 95/O ./O Red/O race/O 18/O \*/O ,/O 34/O \*/O ,/O 35/O ,/O 143/O ./O Red/O river/O 131/O ./O Red/O river/O prairies/O 77/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 113/O ./O Red/O sea/O 179/O ./O Reindeer/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 56/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Relief/O maps/O ,/O Africa/LOCATION 176/O ./O Animal/O realms/O 43/O ./O Asia/LOCATION 160/O ./O Australia/LOCATION 184/O ./O Europe/LOCATION 146/O ./O North/LOCATION America/LOCATION 62/O ./O Primary/O highland/O 14/O ./O Races/O 35/O ./O South/LOCATION America/LOCATION 136/O ./O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 68-69/O ./O World/O 2/O ,/O 14/O ./O Religions/O 39/O ,/O 40/O \*/O ;/O see/O topics/O ,/O People/O ./O Reno/PERSON 117/O ,/O 119/O ./O Republics/O 41/O ./O Reservations/O 34/O ./O Revolution/O of/O earth/O 25/O ./O Rhea/PERSON 142/O \*/O ./O Rhine/LOCATION river/O 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Rhinoceros/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 142/O \*/O ,/O 182/O \*/O ./O Rhode/LOCATION Island/LOCATION ,/O 88-91/O ./O Rhone/O river/O 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Rice/O 46/O ,/O 47/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 99,124/O ,/O 169/O ,/O 174/O ,/O 181/O ./O Richmond/ORGANIZATION 78/O ,/O 93/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Riga/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Rio/LOCATION de/LOCATION Janeiro/LOCATION 139,143/O \*/O ./O Rio/LOCATION Grande/LOCATION 105/O ./O Rio/LOCATION Negro/LOCATION 139/O ./O River/O 5/O \*/O ,/O 6/O ,/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 8/O \*/O ,/O 29/O \*/O ,/O 99/O \*/O ./O Roanoke/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Rochester/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O Rockford/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Rocky/O mts/O ./O 17/O \*/O ,/O 66/O \*/O ./O Rocky/O mountain/O highland/O 17/O \*/O ,/O 64/O ,/O 66/O \*/O ./O Rome/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 158/O \*/O ./O Rosin/O 49/O \*/O ./O Rotation/O of/O earth/O 3/O ./O Rotterdam/LOCATION 156/O \*/O ,/O 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Roumania/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Roumelia/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Routes/O of/O trade/O 1900/O ,/O 1910/O ./O Rubber/O :/O see/O India/LOCATION rubber/O ./O Russia/LOCATION 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 150/O \*/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Russian/O empire/O 159/O ./O Rutland/LOCATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Rye/O 78/O ./O S/O Sable/ORGANIZATION 87/O \*/O ./O Sacramento/LOCATION 117/O ,/O 120/O ./O Saginaw/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Sago/O 44/O ./O Sahara/ORGANIZATION 22/O ,/O 30/O \*/O ,/O 178/O \*/O ,/O 179/O ./O Saigon/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O St./PERSON Albans/PERSON 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O St./O Augustine/O 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O St./O Croix/O 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O St./O Gotthard/O 145/O ,/O 147/O ./O St./LOCATION Helena/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O St./O John/PERSON ,/O city/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O St./O John/PERSON ,/O island/O 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O St./O Johns/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O St./LOCATION Joseph/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O St./LOCATION Lawrence/LOCATION river/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 20/O ./O St./LOCATION Louis/LOCATION 77/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 112/O \*/O ,/O 113/O ./O St./O Marys/O river/O 107/O \*/O ./O St./LOCATION Paul/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O St./LOCATION Peter/LOCATION 's/O 158/O ./O St./LOCATION Petersburg/LOCATION 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O St./LOCATION Thomas/LOCATION 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O Salem/LOCATION ,/O Ore./LOCATION 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Salmon/O 82/O ,/O 119/O ./O Saloniki/PERSON 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Salt/O 110/O ./O Salt/O desert/O 163/O ./O Salt/LOCATION Lake/LOCATION City/LOCATION 116/O \*/O ,/O 117/O ,/O 118/O \*/O ./O Salt/O lakes/O 6/O ./O Salvador/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O Samoa/O 126/O ,/O 187/O ./O San/LOCATION Antonio/LOCATION 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Sandstone/O 58/O ,/O 89/O ./O Sandwich/O islands/O ;/O see/O Hawaii/LOCATION ./O San/LOCATION Francisco/LOCATION 117/O ,/O 120/O ./O San/LOCATION Francisco/LOCATION river/O 139/O ,/O 140/O ./O San/LOCATION Jose/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 133/O ./O San/LOCATION Juan/LOCATION 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O San/LOCATION Marino/LOCATION 145/O ,/O 157/O ./O San/LOCATION Salvador/LOCATION 131/O ./O Santa/O Clara/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Santa/O Fe/O 116/O ,/O 117/O ./O Santiago/LOCATION ,/O Chile/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 143/O \*/O ,/O 144/O ./O Santiago/LOCATION ,/O Cuba/LOCATION 134/O \*/O ,/O 135/O ./O Santo/PERSON Domingo/PERSON 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Santos/ORGANIZATION 139/O ,/O 143/O ./O Saone/O river/O 157/O ./O Sardinia/LOCATION 157/O ./O Saskatchewan/LOCATION 131/O ./O Savannah/ORGANIZATION 76/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Scandinavian/O peninsula/O 20/O ,/O 147/O ,/O 148/O ./O Scotland/LOCATION 38/O \*/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 155/O ;/O see/O also/O British/O Isles/O ./O Scranton/LOCATION 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Sea/O 12/O ./O Sea-bottom/O 15/O ./O Sea/O of/O Azof/O 149/O ./O Sea/O of/O Galilee/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 164/O ./O Seal/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 56/O ,/O 122/O ,/O 165/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Seashells/O 8/O ./O Seasons/O 25/O ,/O 26/O ,/O 27/O ,/O 28/O ./O Seattle/LOCATION 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Seine/LOCATION river/O 157/O ./O Selma/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Selvas/O 18/O \*/O ,/O 19/O ,/O 137/O ,/O 140/O ./O Semites/O 38/O ,/O 39/O \*/O ./O Seoul/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Servia/PERSON 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Shanghai/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Shannon/PERSON river/O 155/O ./O Sheep/O 54/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 159/O ,/O 164/O ,/O 181/O ,/O 188/O ./O 189/O ./O Sheffield/ORGANIZATION 154/O ,/O 155/O ./O Shenandoah/ORGANIZATION 93/O ,/O 95/O ./O Shetland/O islands/O 155/O ./O Shoshone/O falls/O 118/O ,/O 120/O \*/O ./O Shreveport/LOCATION 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Siam/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Siberia/ORGANIZATION 20/O ,/O 21/O ,/O 37/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 163/O ,/O 174/O ./O Siberian/O railroad/O 165/O ./O Sicily/LOCATION 157/O ./O Sierra/LOCATION Leone/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Sierra/ORGANIZATION Madre/ORGANIZATION 17/O ,/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Sierra/ORGANIZATION Nevada/ORGANIZATION 63/O ,/O 66/O ,/O 70/O ,/O 119/O ./O Silk/O 97/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 172/O ./O Silver/O 58/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 115/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 118/O ,/O 119/O ,/O 132/O ,/O 144/O ./O Simoon/O 181/O ./O Singapore/LOCATION 168/O \*/O ,/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Sioux/LOCATION City/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Sioux/LOCATION Falls/O 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Sisal/O hemp/O 132/O ./O Sitka/LOCATION 122/O \*/O ,/O 123/O ./O Size/O of/O earth/O 21/O ./O Slate/O 59/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 89/O ./O Slave/O coast/O 22/O ./O Smelting/O 56/O ./O Smyrna/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Snake/O river/O 121/O ./O Snow/O mts/O ./O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O ``/O Soo/O ''/O canal/O 107/O ./O Source/O 6/O \*/O ./O South/LOCATION America/LOCATION 18/O ,/O 19/O ./O Animals/O 142/O ./O Climate/O 141/O ./O Countries/O 143/O ./O People/O 142/O ./O Plants/O 141/O ./O Political/O map/O 139/O ./O Relief/O map/O 18/O ,/O 136/O ./O Surface/O 18/O ,/O 137-141/O ./O South/LOCATION Australia/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O South/O Bend/O 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O South/ORGANIZATION Carolina/ORGANIZATION 76/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 98-101/O ./O South/LOCATION Dakota/LOCATION 77/O ,/O 111-113/O ,/O 114/O ./O South/LOCATION Omaha/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Southern/O plain/O 17/O ;/O see/O Gulf/O coastal/O plain/O ./O Southern/O states/O 98-101/O ,/O 105/O ./O Spain/LOCATION 147/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 158/O ./O Spartanburg/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Sphinx/O 177/O \*/O ,/O 178/O ./O Spices/O 45/O \*/O ,/O 46/O \*/O ,/O 164/O ./O Spitzbergen/LOCATION 163/O ./O Spokane/LOCATION 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Spring/O 5/O ./O Springfield/LOCATION ,/O Ill./LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Springfield/LOCATION ,/O Mass./LOCATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Springfield/LOCATION ,/O Mo./LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Springfield/LOCATION ,/O Ohio/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Staked/O plain/O 70/O ,/O 103/O ./O Standard/O time/O 192/O ./O Stanovoi/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 173/O ./O Steamships/O 1/O \*/O ,/O 60/O \*/O ./O Steel/O 56/O \*/O ;/O see/O Iron/O ./O Steppes/O 21/O ,/O 81/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 161/O ,/O 165/O \*/O ./O Stockholm/O 149/O ,/O 159/O ./O Strait/O of/O Dover/LOCATION 155/O ./O Strait/O of/O Gibraltar/LOCATION 149/O ./O Strait/O of/O Magellan/O 139/O ./O Straits/O Settlements/O 173/O ,/O 174/O ./O Sucre/O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Sudan/ORGANIZATION 22/O ,/O 178/O ,/O 179/O ./O Suez/ORGANIZATION 14/O ,/O 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Sugar/O 46/O \*/O ,/O 47/O \*/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 96/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 123/O ,/O 124/O ,/O 125/O ,/O 126/O ,/O 134/O \*/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 181/O ./O Sugar/O beets/O 85/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 158/O ,/O 159/O ./O Suliman/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 173/O ./O Sumatra/LOCATION 167/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 187/O ./O Sun/O 2/O ,/O 25/O ,/O 26/O ./O Superior/O 109/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 114/O ./O Susquehanna/O river/O 95/O ./O Sweden/LOCATION 148/O ,/O 149/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 159/O ./O Switzerland/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Sydney/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 188/O ./O Syracuse/ORGANIZATION 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O T/O Table/O mountain/O 180/O ./O Tabriz/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Tacoma/LOCATION 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Tahlequah/LOCATION 105/O ,/O 106/O ./O Tallahassee/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Tampa/O 78/O ,/O 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Tapir/O 142/O \*/O ,/O 171/O \*/O ./O Tartars/O 153/O ./O Tashkend/O 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Tasmania/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 188/O ./O Tea/O 46/O \*/O ,/O 169/O ,/O 172/O ,/O 174/O ./O Teak/O 169/O ./O Teheran/LOCATION 173/O ,/O 175/O ./O Tehuantepec/LOCATION 131/O ./O Telegraph/ORGANIZATION 60/O ./O Telephone/O 60/O ./O Temperate/O zones/O 27/O ,/O 28/O ,/O 47/O \*/O -51/O \*/O ./O Tennessee/LOCATION 83/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Tennessee/LOCATION river/O 105/O ./O Terre/O Haute/O 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Territories/O 128/O ./O Texas/LOCATION 70/O ,/O 76/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 80/O ,/O 83/O ,/O 85/O ,/O 86/O ,/O 103/O ,/O 104/O ,/O 105/O ./O Thames/O river/O 41/O \*/O ./O The/O Hague/ORGANIZATION 157/O ,/O 158/O ./O Thousand/O Isles/O 131/O ./O Tiber/O 145/O ,/O 149/O ./O Tibet/ORGANIZATION 21/O ,/O 161/O ./O Tides/O 11/O ,/O 12/O \*/O ./O Tiflis/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Tiger/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 171/O \*/O ./O Tigris/LOCATION river/O 164/O ,/O 173/O ./O Timbuktu/LOCATION 179/O ./O Time/O belts/O 192/O ./O Tin/O 96/O ,/O 168/O ,/O 188/O ./O Titicaca/LOCATION ,/O lake/O 18/O ,/O 19/O ,/O 138/O \*/O ,/O 139/O ./O Tobacco/O 47/O ,/O 48/O ,/O 49/O \*/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 110/O ,/O 134/O ,/O 152/O ./O Tokyo/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Toledo/O 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Tonga/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Tonkin/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Topeka/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Toronto/LOCATION 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Torrid/O zone/O 24/O \*/O ,/O 28/O ,/O 44/O \*/O ./O Toulouse/LOCATION 156/O ,/O 157/O ./O Tower/O of/O London/LOCATION 153/O \*/O ./O Trade/O highways/O 190-191/O ./O Trade/O winds/O 30/O ,/O 31/O ./O Trans-Caucasia/O 163/O ./O Transvaal/ORGANIZATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Tree/O ferns/O 167/O \*/O ./O Trenton/ORGANIZATION 93/O ,/O 95/O ,/O 96/O \*/O ,/O 97/O ./O Trieste/ORGANIZATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Trinidad/LOCATION 139/O ./O Tripoli/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 183/O ,/O 184/O ./O Tropics/ORGANIZATION 25/O ,/O 27/O ./O Tsetse/O fly/O 182/O \*/O ./O Tucson/LOCATION 117/O ,/O 119/O ./O Tundras/O 21/O ,/O 52/O \*/O ,/O 151/O ,/O 161/O ./O Tunis/LOCATION 179/O ,/O 184/O ./O Turkestan/LOCATION 163/O ./O Turkey/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ,/O 163/O ,/O 164/O ,/O 175/O ./O Turks/O 153/O ./O Turpentine/O 49/O ./O Tutuila/O 126/O ,/O 187/O ./O U/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION States/ORGANIZATION 61/O \*/O -128/O ./O Animals/O 86/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Area/O 61/O ./O Boundary/O 72-73/O ./O Cities/O 89-120/O ./O Climate/O 74/O ,/O 75/O ./O Commerce/O 76-87/O ;/O see/O various/O seaports/O ./O Government/O 128/O ./O Indians/ORGANIZATION 34/O \*/O ,/O 35/O ,/O 62/O ./O Negroes/O 63/O ./O People/O 61/O ,/O 63/O ,/O 64/O ./O Population/O 64/O ;/O see/O Sup/O ./O Products/O 76/O \*/O -87/O \*/O ,/O 88-127/O ./O Relief/O map/O 68-69/O ./O States/LOCATION 88-120/O ./O Surface/O 64-71/O ./O Ural/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 149/O ,/O 150/O ./O Ural/O river/O 149/O ./O Uruguay/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Utah/LOCATION 116/O ,/O 117/O ,/O 118/O ./O V/O Valdai/ORGANIZATION hills/O 149/O ./O Valdosta/LOCATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Valencia/LOCATION ,/O Sp/LOCATION ./O 149/O ,/O 158/O ./O Valencia/LOCATION ,/O Ven/LOCATION ./O 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Valleys/O 9/O \*/O ./O Valparaiso/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Vancouver/LOCATION 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Vanilla/O 45/O ./O Vapor/O 29/O ./O Vatican/O 158/O ./O Vegetables/O 50/O ,/O 51/O \*/O ,/O 86/O ./O Venezuela/LOCATION 139/O ,/O 144/O ./O Venice/ORGANIZATION 149/O ,/O 152/O ,/O 158/O \*/O ./O Vera/PERSON Cruz/PERSON 131/O ,/O 132/O \*/O ,/O 133/O ./O Vermont/ORGANIZATION 86/O ,/O 88/O \*/O ,/O 91/O ./O Vesuvius/O 11/O \*/O ,/O 147/O \*/O ,/O 149/O ./O Vicksburg/LOCATION 101/O ,/O 102/O ./O Victoria/LOCATION ,/O Aus/LOCATION ./O 187/O ,/O 188/O ./O Victoria/LOCATION ,/O B./PERSON C./PERSON 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Victoria/LOCATION falls/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Victoria/LOCATION Nyanza/LOCATION 177/O ,/O 179/O ./O Vieques/O 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O Vienna/LOCATION 157/O ,/O 159/O ./O Virginia/LOCATION 78/O ,/O 79/O ,/O 92-95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Virginia/LOCATION ,/O city/O 117/O ,/O 119/O ./O Virgin/O islands/O 126/O ,/O 135/O ./O Vladivostok/LOCATION 163/O ,/O 175/O ./O Vocabulary/O ;/O Sup/O ./O vi-viii/O ./O Volcanic/O islands/O 189/O ./O Volcanoes/O 11/O \*/O ,/O 122/O ,/O 167/O ,/O 168/O ./O Volga/LOCATION river/O 149/O ,/O 151/O ./O W/O Wake/O island/O 126/O ,/O 127/O ./O Wales/LOCATION 151/O ,/O 155/O ;/O see/O also/O British/O Isles/O ./O Walrus/O 56/O ,/O 87/O \*/O ./O Wasatch/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 70/O ./O Washington/LOCATION ,/O city/O 95/O ,/O 98/O ,/O 128/O ./O Washington/LOCATION ,/O state/O 119/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 121/O ./O Water/O 2/O ,/O 6/O ./O Waterbury/LOCATION ,/O 91/O ,/O 92/O ./O Waterfalls/O 7/O ./O Waterloo/LOCATION 157/O ./O Water/O parting/O 7/O Water/O routes/O 190-191/O ./O Waterspout/O 30/O \*/O ./O Waves/O 2/O \*/O ,/O 5/O \*/O ,/O 7/O \*/O ,/O 11/O ,/O 12/O ./O Welland/O canal/O 94/O ,/O 107/O ./O Wellington/LOCATION 187/O ,/O 189/O ./O Westerly/O winds/O 31/O ./O Western/O Australia/LOCATION 187/O ./O Western/O Ghats/O 173/O ./O Western/O highland/O ;/O see/O Rocky/LOCATION mountain/O highland/O ./O Western/O plains/O 17/O ,/O 70/O ./O Western/O states/O 115-117-121/O ./O West/O Indies/O 18/O ,/O 65/O ,/O 78/O ,/O 133/O ,/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O West/O Point/O 95/O ,/O 96/O ./O West/LOCATION Virginia/LOCATION 83/O ,/O 92-95/O ,/O 98/O ./O Whale/O 54/O \*/O ,/O 56/O ./O Wheat/O 50/O \*/O ,/O 77/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 114/O ,/O 119/O ,/O 120/O ,/O 141/O ,/O 144/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 159/O ,/O 174/O ,/O 169/O ,/O 181/O ,/O 186/O ,/O 188/O ./O Wheeling/O 950/O 98/O ./O White/O mts/O ./O 65/O ,/O 67/O \*/O ,/O 88/O ,/O 89/O \*/O ./O White/O Nile/O 179/O ./O White/O race/O 35/O ,/O 38/O \*/O ,/O 188/O ./O White/O sea/O 149/O ./O Wichita/LOCATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Willamette/ORGANIZATION valley/O 121/O ./O Wilmington/LOCATION ,/O Del./O 95/O ,/O 97/O ./O Wilmington/LOCATION ,/O N./PERSON C./PERSON 76/O ,/O 99/O ,/O 101/O ./O Wind/O River/O ruts/O ./O 121/O ./O Winds/O 11/O ,/O 29/O ,/O 30/O ,/O 31/O ,/O 74/O ./O Windward/O islands/O 134/O ,/O 135/O ./O Wine/O 152/O ,/O 156/O ,/O 158/O ./O Winnipeg/LOCATION 130/O ,/O 131/O ./O Winona/ORGANIZATION 113/O ,/O 114/O ./O Winston/ORGANIZATION 100/O ,/O 101/O ./O Wisconsin/LOCATION 106-109/O ,/O 111/O ./O Wolf/O 55/O \*/O ./O Wool/O ;/O see/O Sheep/O ./O Woolly/O elephants/O 165/O ./O Woonsocket/ORGANIZATION 91/O ./O Worcester/ORGANIZATION 90/O ,/O 91/O ./O Wyoming/ORGANIZATION 11/O \*/O ,/O 115/O ,/O 116/O ,/O 121/O ./O Y/O Yablonoi/ORGANIZATION mts/ORGANIZATION ./O 163/O ./O Yak/O 20/O \*/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 170/O \*/O ./O Yangtze/O river/O 166/O ,/O 173/O ./O Yarkand/O 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Yazoo/ORGANIZATION 78/O \*/O ,/O 99/O ./O Yellow/O pine/O 49/O ,/O 79/O ./O Yellow/O race/O 35/O ,/O 36/O ,/O 37/O \*/O ./O Yellow/O river/O 166/O \*/O ,/O 173/O ./O Yellowstone/O park/O 115/O \*/O ,/O 121/O ./O Yenisei/LOCATION river/O 163/O ./O Yokohama/LOCATION 172/O ,/O 173/O ./O Yosemite/O valley/O 119/O \*/O ,/O 121/O ./O Youngstown/LOCATION 109/O ,/O 110/O ./O Yucatan/O 131/O ,/O 132/O ./O Yukon/O river/O 123/O ./O Z/O Zambezi/ORGANIZATION river/O 179/O ,/O 180/O ./O Zebra/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 182/O ./O Zebu/O 54/O ,/O 55/O \*/O ,/O 171/O \*/O ./O Zinc/O 85/O ,/O 107/O ,/O 111/O ,/O 114/O ,/O 148/O ,/O 150/O ,/O Zones/O 27/O ,/O 28/O ./O Zones/O of/O animal/O life/O 53-55/O ./O Zones/O of/O plant/O life/O 42-52/O ./O Zuni/O 34/O \*/O ./O Zurich/O 157/O ,/O 159/O \*/O ./O INTRODUCTION/O GEOGRAPHY/O Geography/O is/O the/O study/O of/O the/O earth/O as/O the/O home/O of/O man/O ./O We/O can/O not/O visit/O all/O parts/O of/O the/O earth/O ,/O such/O as/O the/O wide/O snow/O fields/O of/O the/O far/O north/O ,/O where/O the/O Eskimos/O hunt/O the/O white/O bear/O and/O the/O seal/O for/O food/O ;/O the/O great/O forests/O into/O which/O men/O go/O to/O cut/O down/O trees/O for/O lumber/O ;/O the/O broad/O grassy/O plains/O where/O herdsmen/O tend/O cattle/O and/O sheep/O ;/O the/O fertile/O fields/O white/O with/O cotton/O or/O blue/O with/O flax/O ;/O the/O far-off/O lands/O where/O people/O feed/O silkworms/O on/O mulberry/O leaves/O and/O where/O the/O worms/O spin/O their/O soft/O homes/O of/O silken/O fiber/O ;/O the/O deep/O holes/O in/O the/O earth/O where/O miners/O dig/O coal/O or/O iron/O ore/O out/O of/O the/O beds/O of/O rock/O ./O Nor/O can/O we/O visit/O all/O the/O great/O workshops/O To/O TEACHERS/O :/O The/O preface/O of/O this/O book/O should/O be/O read/O very/O carefully/O by/O every/O teacher/O ,/O especially/O the/O topics/O referring/O to/O sizes/O of/O type/O ,/O spelling/O ,/O etc./O and/O busy/O mills/O in/O large/O cities/O ,/O where/O workmen/O carve/O and/O smooth/O the/O rough/O wood/O into/O beautiful/O furniture/O ;/O or/O weave/O the/O fibers/O of/O cotton/O and/O silk/O into/O fine/O cloth/O ;/O or/O melt/O the/O ore/O of/O the/O deep/O mines/O ,/O change/O it/O to/O iron/O or/O steel/O and/O shape/O it/O into/O machinery/O and/O ships/O ./O We/O may/O perhaps/O visit/O some/O of/O these/O ,/O but/O we/O can/O see/O pictures/O of/O many/O more/O ./O We/O can/O also/O study/O maps/O and/O find/O out/O where/O people/O have/O built/O their/O cities/O ,/O whether/O in/O cold/O lands/O or/O in/O warm/O lands/O ,/O on/O mountains/O or/O on/O plains/O ,/O near/O the/O ocean/O or/O far/O inland/O ,/O in/O deserts/O or/O in/O lands/O through/O which/O flow/O wide/O and/O deep/O rivers/O ./O We/O can/O read/O about/O the/O busy/O workshops/O ,/O the/O rushing/O streams/O that/O turn/O mill/O wheels/O ,/O the/O fields/O that/O supply/O fibers/O for/O swift/O looms/O ,/O the/O high/O mountains/O that/O help/O to/O make/O rain/O and/O snow/O fall/O from/O the/O clouds/O ,/O the/O wide/O and/O deep/O oceans/O that/O carry/O steamships/O loaded/O with/O freight/O from/O port/O to/O port/O ,/O the/O swift/O trains/O that/O speed/O from/O city/O to/O city/O ./O We/O can/O also/O read/O about/O famous/O galleries/O of/O paintings/O and/O statues/O ./O All/O this/O is/O geography/O ,/O the/O study/O of/O the/O earth/O as/O the/O home/O of/O man/O ./O THE/ORGANIZATION EARTH/ORGANIZATION 1/O ./O Form/O and/O Size/O of/O the/O Earth/LOCATION The/O earth/O is/O a/O great/O ball/O of/O land/O and/O water/O ,/O with/O air/O around/O it/O on/O all/O sides/O ./O The/O greater/O part/O of/O the/O land/O is/O rock/O ,/O but/O a/O thin/O layer/O of/O the/O outside/O of/O the/O rock/O has/O crumbled/O into/O gravel/O ,/O sand/O or/O finer/O soil/O ./O There/O is/O solid/O rock/O everywhere/O under/O the/O soil/O and/O under/O all/O the/O waters/O of/O the/O earth/O ,/O but/O in/O most/O places/O layers/O of/O fine/O mud/O have/O settled/O on/O the/O rock/O under/O the/O water/O ./O Most/O of/O the/O plants/O that/O yield/O us/O food/O grow/O in/O the/O layer/O of/O soil/O over/O the/O rock/O ./O In/O some/O places/O the/O bare/O rock/O comes/O to/O the/O surface/O ./O Nearly/O all/O deep/O mines/O are/O in/O firm/O rock/O ,/O and/O here/O are/O found/O most/O of/O the/O coal/O ,/O iron/O ore/O ,/O copper/O ,/O gold/O and/O other/O minerals/O useful/O to/O man/O ./O Very/O deep/O mines/O show/O us/O that/O the/O inside/O of/O the/O earth/O ,/O far/O below/O the/O surface/O ,/O must/O be/O very/O hot/O ./O Rocks/O jutting/O out/O of/O the/O ocean/O As/O such/O mines/O are/O dug/O deeper/O the/O heat/O increases/O ./O It/O is/O believed/O that/O the/O earth/O was/O once/O much/O hotter/O than/O it/O is/O now/O ,/O and/O that/O as/O it/O cooled/O it/O shrank/O away/O faster/O in/O some/O places/O than/O in/O others/O and/O thus/O made/O wrinkles/O like/O those/O on/O a/O withered/O apple/O ./O The/O higher/O wrinkles/O of/O the/O earth/O are/O now/O the/O land/O ./O Wide/O hollows/O between/O the/O wrinkles/O are/O filled/O with/O the/O salt/O water/O of/O the/O sea/O ./O The/O surface/O of/O the/O land/O is/O not/O smooth/O ,/O but/O has/O wide/O hollows/O or/O valleys/O in/O which/O the/O waters/O of/O the/O sea/O collect/O ./O Nearly/O three/O fourths/O of/O the/O surface/O of/O the/O earth/O are/O covered/O with/O water/O that/O lies/O in/O these/O broad/O valleys/O ./O The/O dry/O land/O consists/O of/O the/O higher/O parts/O that/O rise/O above/O the/O level/O of/O the/O water/O in/O the/O great/O valleys/O ./O The/O little/O maps/O on/O this/O page/O show/O the/O two/O sides/O of/O the/O round/O earth/O ./O The/O dark/O rough/O parts/O are/O the/O land/O ;/O the/O other/O parts/O are/O water/O ./O The/O maps/O do/O not/O show/O the/O lands/O that/O lie/O under/O the/O water/O ./O We/O live/O on/O the/O land/O ,/O but/O the/O great/O bodies/O of/O water/O also/O are/O very/O useful/O to/O man/O ./O They/O supply/O the/O water/O for/O rain/O ,/O and/O they/O carry/O ships/O loaded/O with/O goods/O from/O seaport/O to/O seaport/O ./O We/O see/O so/O small/O a/O part/O of/O the/O earth/O at/O a/O time/O that/O it/O does/O not/O look/O round/O ,/O but/O there/O are/O many/O proofs/O that/O it/O has/O this/O form/O ./O Here/O are/O a/O few/O of/O the/O proofs/O :/O 1/O ./O Many/O persons/O have/O gone/O round/O the/O earth/O ./O 2/O ./O The/O smoke/O of/O steamers/O at/O sea/O can/O be/O seen/O long/O before/O the/O hulls/O come/O in/O sight/O above/O the/O sky/O line/O ,/O or/O horizon/O ./O 3/O ./O When/O travelers/O go/O day/O after/O day/O towards/O the/O north/O or/O the/O south/O new/O stars/O rise/O over/O the/O horizon/O before/O them/O ,/O while/O the/O stars/O behind/O sink/O slowly/O out/O of/O sight/O ./O 4/O ./O Sometimes/O the/O earth/O moves/O between/O the/O sun/O and/O the/O moon/LOCATION and/O casts/O a/O shadow/O on/O the/O moon/LOCATION ./O The/O edge/O of/O this/O shadow/O always/O looks/O like/O part/O of/O a/O circle/O ./O The/O sun/O and/O the/O moon/O are/O round/O ,/O like/O the/O earth/O ./O The/O moon/O is/O smaller/O than/O the/O earth/O ,/O but/O the/O sun/O is/O many/O times/O larger/O ./O The/O sun/O lights/O and/O warms/O the/O earth/O ./O The/O sun/O also/O lights/O the/O bright/O face/O of/O the/O moon/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O moon/LOCATION reflects/O some/O of/O the/O light/O to/O the/O earth/O ./O The/O great/O round/O earth/O curves/O a/O little/O less/O on/O two/O opposite/O sides/O than/O on/O the/O other/O parts/O ./O Sometime/O perhaps/O you/O will/O learn/O how/O this/O slight/O change/O of/O form/O holds/O the/O earth/O in/O one/O position/O ,/O as/O it/O turns/O round/O day/O after/O day/O ,/O and/O thus/O enables/O us/O to/O see/O the/O sun/O ,/O the/O moon/O and/O the/O stars/O in/O the/O same/O place/O in/O the/O sky/O each/O year/O ./O The/O earth/O is/O one/O of/O many/O bodies/O ,/O called/O planets/O ,/O that/O move/O round/O the/O sun/O ./O The/O earth/O goes/O round/O the/O sun/O once/O a/O year/O ./O The/O shadow/O of/O the/O earth/O on/O the/O moon/O is/O called/O an/O eclipse/O of/O the/O moon/LOCATION ./O Sometimes/O the/O moon/O moves/O between/O the/O earth/O and/O the/O sun/O and/O causes/O an/O eclipse/O of/O the/O sun/O ,/O that/O is/O ,/O the/O moon/LOCATION shuts/O off/O a/O part/O or/O the/O whole/O of/O the/O sun/O from/O our/O sight/O ./O The/O diameter/O of/O the/O earth/O ,/O or/O the/O distance/O from/O side/O to/O side/O through/O the/O center/O ,/O is/O nearly/O 8000/O miles/O ./O The/O circumference/O ,/O or/O greatest/O distance/O round/O the/O earth/O ,/O is/O about/O 25,000/O miles/O ./O How/O many/O days/O would/O it/O take/O a/O train/O of/O cars/O ,/O going/O at/O the/O rate/O of/O fifty/O miles/O an/O hour/O ,/O to/O travel/O 25,000/O miles/O ?/O The/O earth/O is/O a/O very/O large/O home/O for/O man/O ./O No/O one/O knows/O just/O how/O high/O the/O layer/O of/O air/O that/O surrounds/O the/O earth/O reaches/O ,/O but/O there/O are/O proofs/O that/O it/O is/O over/O 500/O miles/O above/O our/O heads/O ./O The/O high/O air/O is/O very/O thin/O ,/O or/O rare/O ,/O and/O at/O a/O very/O few/O miles/O from/O the/O surface/O of/O the/O earth/O we/O could/O not/O get/O air/O enough/O to/O breathe/O ./O The/O air/O near/O the/O earth/O is/O more/O dense/O ,/O as/O it/O is/O pressed/O down/O by/O the/O weight/O of/O all/O the/O air/O above/O it/O ./O Helps/O :/O What/O is/O the/O earth/O made/O of/O ?/O What/O is/O its/O form/O ?/O Why/O do/O we/O not/O see/O rocky/O part/O of/O earth/O everywhere/O ?/O What/O is/O under/O all/O bodies/O of/O water/O ?/O Name/O some/O useful/O minerals/O taken/O from/O earth/O ./O What/O do/O plants/O feed/O on/O ?/O What/O do/O deep/O mines/O show/O about/O inside/O of/O earth/O ?/O How/O much/O of/O earth/O 's/O surface/O is/O water/O ?/O Where/O does/O water/O on/O the/O earth/O collect/O ?/O Why/O does/O not/O water/O flow/O over/O whole/O earth/O ?/O Map/O A/O Why/O does/O not/O earth/O look/O like/O ball/O ?/O State/O some/O proofs/O that/O earth/O is/O round/O ./O What/O is/O form/O of/O sun/O and/O moon/LOCATION ?/O Which/O is/O largest/O of/O these/O three/O bodies/O ?/O What/O is/O an/O eclipse/O ?/O What/O is/O meant/O by/O word/O diameter/O ?/O By/O circumference/O ?/O What/O is/O diameter/O of/O earth/O ?/O Circumference/O ?/O Tell/O what/O the/O lesson/O teaches/O about/O the/O air/O ./O Can/O you/O name/O some/O of/O the/O uses/O of/O air/O ?/O Map/O B/O Topics/O :/O Earth/LOCATION 's/O form/O ;/O material/O of/O which/O the/O earth/O is/O made/O ;/O inside/O of/O the/O earth/O ;/O surface/O of/O earth/O ;/O size/O of/O earth/O ;/O sun/O and/O moon/LOCATION ;/O eclipse/O ;/O air/O ./O 2/O ./O Directions/O on/O the/O Earth/LOCATION The/O earth/O is/O always/O turning/O round/O like/O a/O spinning/O top/O ,/O but/O the/O earth/O turns/O only/O once/O in/O twenty-four/O hours/O ,/O or/O a/O day/O and/O a/O night/O ./O This/O spinning/O motion/O is/O called/O the/O rotation/O of/O the/O earth/O ./O The/O sun/O lights/O and/O warms/O one/O half/O of/O the/O earth/O at/O a/O time/O ./O As/O the/O earth/O rotates/O ,/O some/O parts/O of/O it/O are/O turning/O into/O the/O sunlight/O while/O other/O parts/O are/O turning/O away/O from/O it/O into/O the/O dark/O ./O One/O side/O of/O the/O earth/O thus/O has/O day/O while/O the/O other/O side/O has/O night/O ./O Bright/O daylight/O would/O be/O very/O tiresome/O if/O it/O lasted/O all/O the/O time/O ,/O with/O no/O dark/O hours/O for/O rest/O and/O sleep/O ./O Endless/O night/O would/O be/O cold/O Map/O C/O and/O dismal/O ,/O with/O no/O sunshine/O to/O light/O and/O warm/O the/O earth/O ./O Far/O away/O in/O the/O north/O there/O is/O a/O point/O on/O the/O earth/O ,/O known/O as/O the/O north/O pole/O ./O It/O is/O nearly/O under/O the/O north/O star/O ,/O which/O is/O often/O called/O the/O pole/O star/O ./O Opposite/O the/O north/O pole/O ,/O on/O the/O other/O side/O of/O the/O earth/O ,/O there/O is/O a/O point/O called/O the/O south/O pole/O ./O The/O word/O ``/O pole/O ''/O means/O pivot/O ,/O or/O point/O on/O which/O anything/O turns/O ./O The/O earth/O does/O not/O rest/O on/O anything/O ,/O but/O turns/O in/O space/O as/O if/O held/O by/O a/O line/O running/O through/O it/O from/O pole/O to/O pole/O ./O We/O can/O think/O of/O such/O a/O line/O and/O call/O it/O the/O axis/O of/O the/O earth/O ./O The/O poles/O are/O the/O ends/O of/O the/O axis/O ./O To/O TEACHERS/O :/O Strictly/O speaking/O ,/O the/O light/O refracts/O and/O reflects/O slightly/O beyond/O the/O half/O of/O the/O earth/O ,/O but/O this/O need/O not/O be/O taken/O into/O account/O in/O leading/O pupils/O towards/O the/O study/O of/O the/O zones/O of/O light/O and/O heat/O ./O No/O person/O has/O yet/O reached/O the/O poles/O ,/O though/O many/O brave/O men/O have/O tried/O ./O The/O poles/O are/O in/O regions/O where/O ice/O and/O snow/O last/O all/O the/O year/O ./O North/O is/O the/O direction/O towards/O the/O north/O pole/O ;/O south/O ,/O towards/O the/O south/O pole/O ./O All/O lines/O that/O we/O may/O imagine/O running/O north/O on/O the/O earth/O meet/O at/O the/O north/O pole/O ./O All/O lines/O running/O south/O meet/O at/O the/O south/O pole/O ./O East-and-west/O lines/O go/O round/O the/O earth/O in/O circles/O ./O The/O largest/O of/O these/O circles/O is/O midway/O between/O the/O poles/O and/O is/O called/O the/O equator/O ,/O because/O it/O divides/O the/O earth/O into/O two/O equal/O parts/O ./O All/O east-and-west/O lines/O run/O parallel/O with/O the/O equator/O ./O When/O we/O face/O the/O north/O ,/O east/O is/O along/O the/O lines/O to/O the/O right/O ,/O and/O west/O to/O the/O left/O ./O In/O most/O maps/O north/O is/O at/O the/O top/O and/O east/O to/O the/O right/O ,/O but/O this/O is/O not/O true/O of/O all/O maps/O ./O If/O we/O remember/O that/O north/O and/O south/O are/O the/O directions/O towards/O the/O poles/O ,/O while/O east/O and/O west/O are/O Northern/ORGANIZATION and/O southern/O hemispheres/O parallel/O with/O the/O equator/O ,/O it/O will/O be/O easy/O to/O tell/O directions/O on/O all/O maps/O in/O this/O book/O ./O How/O many/O arrows/O on/O map/O A/O point/O north/O ?/O How/O many/O point/O south/O ?/O Which/O arrows/O point/O north/O on/O map/O B/O ?/O On/O map/O C/O ?/O Which/O arrows/O are/O flying/O south/O on/O map/O B/O ?/O On/O map/O C/O ?/O How/O many/O arrows/O on/O map/O A/O point/O east/O ?/O Which/O fly/O east/O on/O map/O B/O ?/O On/O map/O C/O ?/O Which/O arrows/O point/O west/O on/O map/O A/O ?/O On/O map/O B/O ?/O On/O map/O C/O ?/O Of/O course/O there/O are/O no/O real/O circles/O or/O lines/O to/O be/O seen/O running/O round/O the/O earth/O ,/O but/O we/O can/O imagine/O such/O lines/O and/O name/O or/O number/O them/O ./O We/O shall/O find/O that/O these/O lines/O are/O very/O useful/O in/O helping/O to/O locate/O places/O on/O the/O globe/O ,/O just/O as/O we/O locate/O houses/O in/O towns/O or/O cities/O ,/O by/O naming/O streets/O and/O cross/O streets/O ./O The/O equator/O is/O far/O south/O of/O us/O ./O If/O we/O were/O near/O it/O we/O could/O see/O the/O sun/O overhead/O ,/O or/O nearly/O so/O ,/O at/O noon/O every/O clear/O day/O ./O The/O lowlands/O near/O the/O equator/O have/O no/O winter/O ;/O hot/O or/O warm/O weather/O lasts/O all/O the/O year/O ./O Snow/O and/O ice/O are/O not/O found/O in/O that/O part/O of/O the/O world/O ,/O except/O on/O very/O high/O mountains/O ./O Dense/O forests/O cover/O much/O of/O the/O land/O near/O the/O equator/O ./O Birds/O ,/O insects/O and/O large/O animals/O abound/O ./O Most/O of/O the/O insects/O have/O bright/O colors/O ,/O and/O many/O of/O the/O birds/O have/O beautiful/O plumage/O ./O The/O earth/O rotates/O from/O west/O to/O east/O ./O That/O is/O why/O the/O sun/O seems/O to/O rise/O in/O the/O east/O ,/O the/O earth/O turns/O us/O towards/O the/O east/O ./O The/O earth/O is/O a/O globe/O or/O sphere/O ./O One/O half/O the/O earth/O is/O a/O hemisphere/O -LRB-/O hemi/O means/O half/O -RRB-/O ./O The/O equator/O divides/O the/O earth/O into/O a/O northern/O hemisphere/O and/O a/O southern/O hemisphere/O ./O One/O of/O the/O little/O maps/O of/O hemispheres/O on/O this/O page/O shows/O the/O half/O of/O the/O earth/O having/O the/O most/O water/O ;/O the/O other/O shows/O the/O half/O having/O the/O most/O land/O ./O In/O these/O maps/O north/O is/O not/O at/O the/O top/O ,/O but/O is/O at/O the/O point/O where/O the/O north/O lines/O meet/O ./O South/O is/O at/O the/O point/O where/O the/O south/O lines/O meet/O ./O How/O many/O lines/O on/O the/O map/O of/O the/O land/O hemisphere/O are/O drawn/O north/O and/O south/O ?/O Which/O pole/O is/O not/O shown/O on/O this/O map/O ?/O Why/O not/O ?/O By/O means/O of/O the/O sun/O or/O the/O stars/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O by/O the/O mariner/O 's/O compass/O ,/O sailors/O can/O tell/O the/O direction/O in/O which/O they/O are/O going/O ./O Often/O the/O sun/O and/O stars/O are/O not/O in/O sight/O ,/O and/O sailors/O have/O learned/O to/O depend/O mostly/O on/O the/O compass/O ./O Without/O this/O simple/O guide/O the/O task/O of/O steering/O vessels/O from/O port/O to/O port/O would/O be/O very/O difficult/O ./O Here/O is/O a/O picture/O of/O the/O mariner/O 's/O compass/O ./O Under/O its/O glass/O cover/O is/O a/O round/O card/O ,/O naming/O the/O points/O of/O the/O compass/O ,/O north/O ,/O south/O ,/O east/O ,/O west/LOCATION ,/O northeast/LOCATION ,/O etc./O ./O On/O the/O underside/O of/O the/O card/O is/O a/O steel/O magnet/O ,/O in/O the/O form/O of/O a/O thick/O needle/O or/O bar/O ,/O that/O swings/O on/O a/O pivot/O ./O The/O earth/O attracts/O this/O needle/O and/O makes/O it/O point/O almost/O north/O and/O south/O ./O In/O some/O places/O it/O points/O exactly/O north/O and/O south/O ./O Water/O hemisphere/O Land/O hemisphere/O Helps/O :/O What/O is/O meant/O by/O rotation/O ?/O How/O often/O does/O earth/O rotate/O ?/O Explain/O cause/O of/O day/O and/O night/O ./O Mariner/O 's/O compass/O What/O is/O axis/O of/O earth/O ?/O Where/O are/O the/O poles/O ?/O What/O is/O the/O equator/O ?/O What/O is/O meant/O by/O north/O ?/O By/O south/O ?/O By/O east/O Y/O By/O west/O ?/O In/O order/O to/O tell/O directions/O on/O maps/O ,/O what/O must/O we/O remember/O ?/O What/O does/O